[Subtitles: IdioticBaka1824]
STARTING SOON
"Cave Story - Behind the Scenes"
twitter hashtag #uragawa
-Alright, then... shall we get started?
Folks, I'm sure you've all enjoyed some drinks.
-That so?
-Yes.
Okay, should we start?
Let's stand up for this, yeah?
-Sure.
-Yeah.
-Big crowd, huh?
-Yeah, haha.
Man, I'm hella nervous.
-Yeah.
Ok, once again, I'd like to say a few words of introduction.
Uhh,
Folks, I'd like to thank you all for coming to Cave Story's
first talk event, "Cave Story - Behind the Scenes".
I'll be your host for today.
I'm Ikeya Hayato, a game writer.
Thank you for having me.
(applause)
Thank you.
And here we have this event's,
hmm, sponsor? Right,
-Right.
Nakamura, of the company Asterizm.
-Yes. I'm Nakamura, thank you all for coming.
I think today's event will be all sorts of fun.
Thank you for having me.
(applause)
-Well,
Without further ado, well, we can't start without calling on our protagonist,
uhh...
our protagonist, Amaya-san,
and one more guest, without further ado,
I'd like to give them a friendly welcome.
Music!
If you will.
Alright, let's give them a hand!
(applause)
Alright.
Now, today's, uh, main guest,
(it's pretty bright, are you ok?)
-Yep.
is the creator of Cave Story,
Amaya-san of Studio Pixel.
-Yes. I'm Amaya, thank you for having me.
(applause)
And one more person for today's talk,
someone who's very knowledgeable about game development,
an indie game developer like Amaya-san,
we have Naramura-san of Nigoro.
-Naramura here, thank you for having me.
-[applause]
-Without further ado, shall we start the toast?
-Right.
-Yes.
-Uh, how should we do this, guys, can we gokijitsu???
-Okay, everyone...
-Raise our glasses?
???
Okay, why toast then, let's gokijitsu???
-Sure. Raise your glasses please, guys.
-This one?
-Yeah, that.
-"Would you like anything to drink?"
Great, yeah.
Well then, I'd like to toast.
Thank you for Cave Story.
Cheers!
-Cheers!
-Cheeers!
-Cheeeers!
(applause)
-Thank you very much.
Let's sit down, eh?
-Yes. Alright, let's have a seat.
-Well, then.
Without further ado, let's start with Part 1.
First, I'd like to talk with Amaya-san about the,
uh, the development of the project "Cave Story" up until now,
how it went and what it was like.
Amaya-san, please.
-Yes, thank you for asking.
-Well, to get right into it,
About how long has it been since the
final version of Cave Story released?
-Hmm, it's been about 6 years. I released it in 2004.
-2004, huh...
-Yes.
-I see.
Between then and now, it's spread like crazy, right?
-Yeah, I guess.
At that time, I would never have thought it would spread like this.
-Yeah.
Yeah.
-By the way, it was published as a free game in Japan,
-Right.
About how many times has it been downloaded?
-Hmm, well, I haven't exactly been counting, but
it's been put up in various places besides Vector,
[TL note: Vector is a software download site.]
and I've been hosting it on my own site too, um,
And if you put them together, well, Vector is,
-Right.
it's much more than the others.
So that gives an idea of how much it's been downloaded,
about 220,000 times.
-220,000?!
That's amazing.
-You're right.
Yeah.
-In the beginning, when you first released it, how was the reaction?
I guess it felt like it slowly and steadily built up, right?
-Yeah, um,
I wasn't feeling up to polishing the game, but still,
the people who visited my homepage,
you know,
they started spreading it, or should I say, by word of mouth,
-Right.
After that, people went on Vector,
-Hmm.
and, slowly but surely, started downloading from there.
-I see.
A lot of people dropped by on that page,
-Right?
sharing their impressions or reporting bugs...
-Uh-huh.
By the way, folks in the audience,
have you played Cave Story?
-[laughing]
The people who came today...
Uhh, people who've played Cave Story, could you raise your hands?
-Ah, I see.
-Oh, that's awesome.
Pretty much all of them, huh.
-People who've cleared it...?
-People who've cleared it?
Ah, a good number, I see.
-Thank you very much.
Um,
on that note,
the True Ending, or Sacred Grounds... how many have cleared that...?
Oh, that's a lot, haha.
Thank you for clearing it.
-Then I guess we can talk freely, eh?
-Yeah.
-I guess so.
I was a bit worried about spoilers,
but this is a behind-the-scenes event,
-Right.
so let's talk about all kinds of things.
-Yes.
-So, Cave Story is super popular overseas.
-Ah, yes it is.
So it seems, but how exactly did it spread?
-Hmm, so about that, you see...
I... did think about translating it to English,
I'd been receiving a lot of emails asking about a translation,
-I see. From yuu tao???, I presume?
-That's right, from fans,
who asked if I could translate it.
Now, I did try, but...
Making it in English, you know...
Uh, there's a lot of,
It's not just replacing the text,
-Yeah.
but the characters, they need to line up exactly,
-Ah, yes.
which was hard, it was a little discouraging.
At that point, a person called Shih Tzu reached out, saying he would make
an English translation, as opposed to a localisation.
[TL note: I'm still not too sure about the two words he used here.]
-A localisation is different from a translation?
-That's right. A translation is,
almost entirely left up to the translator,
-Ok.
There was, well, a group that made, uh, a patch.
-Ohh.
I didn't really have to do anything myself.
-I see.
They had a group that did it all on their own.
-Huh.
So I got acquainted with Shih Tzu-san,
-Right. So this person called Shih Tzu-san did it?
-That's right, yes.
Thanks to him, it spread overseas,
-I see.
which was really cool.
-Now, in Japan, Cave Story is known as a free game,
-Yes.
but overseas, it's been ported to various hardware, right?
-Ah, you're right. Um,
Uh, the WiiWare,
-There's a WiiWare port, right?
-Yes... also the DSi...
-I see.
-It's on the screen, see.
-Oh, it's on the screen, right?
So this here,
From left to right, um,
nan kishibou??? arun desuka ne, kore wa
-Here, the first one, that's the original, right?
-The Windows version.
-Yes, that's the original.
-Yes.
-The one in the middle is the Mac version.
-Mac version... Ah.
-The Mac version, well, I have a friend called Nakiwo,
who,
he developed programs for Mac,
and he said he wanted to make a port,
"I want to program a port", he said, and immediately afterward,
he was like, "I ported it."
-Huh.
-Yes.
-The users (???)
-Right. It was only on Windows,
and I'd resigned myself to that,
but thanks to him, the game spread to Mac users too.
-Hmm.
-What's the one on the far right?
-The one on the right is, uh, the English version.
-Right, the English version.
-The English version has "Cave Story",
written in English on it.
So the title, logo, and all that was all converted to English, you see.
-Huh.
-So Doukutsu Monogatari is known overseas as "Cave Story", is it?
-That's right, "Cave Story".
Just kinda-
-kinda literal, eh?
-Yeah.
-Next, the first on the bottom right, uh,
-Let's see...
it looks kinda, polygon-ish, right?
-This is from the 3DS.
-Oh.
Yeah.
-About how much longer will it be for the 3DS release overseas?
-Uh, I think it should be this month...
-Soon, right?
Right.
-Next week, right? I think it was... November 8.
-Yes.
-Oh, that's right.
Soon.
-Right. And this one here is,
the WiiWare version.
-Yes.
-Ah, yes. For the upgraded visuals,
the graphics were drawn in double [resolution],
that's what happened in the WiiWare version.
-So the graphics were edited...
-The graphics, and...
the, um...
The soundtrack was, uh,
it was remixed...
-Ah, the soundtrack is different too?
-That's right, yes.
It wasn't me, though,
a professional was doing the remixing.
-Hmm.
-Now, the Mac port, and the English version, and such,
Those fell in the free category, which isn't surprising...
-Yeah.
But I was surprised that the WiiWare and 3DS versions
-You're right!
were commercial releases, that was quite the shock,
-Yes.
So, what has your release schedule been like since then?
-Well, let's see. Cave Story is, you know,
there are a lot of players, and the fans are increasing,
Since then I've worked on some minigames, but...
"I have been busy, and haven't been able to do much,
"so right now, I can't release anything, please be patient,
"let me recover my strength," is what it was like... But,
well,
around then, Tyrone Rodriguez of Nicalis,
-The president of "Nicalis"?
-That's right. So I heard from Tyrone,
via email,
that he wanted to make a mobile port of Cave Story.
And that he'd ported Yie Ar Kung-Fu to mobile already.
-Right.
By mobile, you mean mobile phone.
-Ah, yes, mobile phone.
Mobile phone?
-That's right.
And I thought, an action game like this
on a mobile phone? No way.
-You're right, yeah.
-I wondered, what sort of person are you?
After that,
Well, I was busy at that time,
and it looked like he could do it if I left it up to him,
-Right.
so I let him do it.
And then, well...
Um, for a while,
Having given him approval, I was wondering what would happen,
but then I didn't hear from him at all,
-Huh? Even though he suggested it first?
-Yeah, you're right.
So I thought, "I guess that's just how it is,"
and I gave up on the mobile, and then came the GameBoy Advance...
-Oh, you gave up on the mobile port?
-Yeah, I guess I gave up...
...is what I thought at the time,
-I see.
-So, uh,
???
-the GameBoy Advance...
Yes?
Ah, but,
I guess I didn't really mind that...
-Really?
-Oh, haha.
With the DS and Wii thing after that...
-It kept climbing higher, eh?
Exactly! Bit by bit, kinda...
It was almost like a dream, you could say...
-Yeah.
Really, such ??? - On the contrary,
I thought doing something like that was impossible, but...
Well, it's been a few years since, but finally,
it came out on WiiWare overseas.
-Right.
-I see.
So about the WiiWare release, this Tyrone-san from Nicalis,
-Yes.
-Hm?
he handled all of that himself?
-That's right.
I see...
Amaya-san, you're not really the sort of person who can depend on others, right?
-Ah, well... Actually, that's how it was at first...
-Right.
But in the end, all this going back and forth, I didn't really like it...
-Hmm.
-Oh, right, the WiiWare sprites were redrawn, weren't they?
-So...
-That's right. So there, in the end,
there was a lot of this and that to do,
a bunch of stuff popping up they'd ask me to do,
and such - I couldn't do all of it ???
...that's how it was...
jihoku??? kosoku kara iro iro kakawari nagara shigoto ??? koto de
-Speaking of which, the 3DS version is releasing soon overseas,
-Right.
but what sort of commercial release did Cave Story see over there?
-So about that... WiiWare de tsukutteruyo to itteru koro kara desu ne ichiyou
The 3D modeling and such, when it came to us...
-Ah, the modeling ??? since then?
-That's right. So, um,
Well, this was games, not work - that sort of an atmosphere, so...
-Uh-huh.
but eventually, I guess it was like, I'm not making decisions on my own, am I?
Yeah.
So things like that happened...
Also, really, what would it look like in 3D...
I could hardly even imagine it.
-Right...
-Yeah...
Also, nanda kanda to itte, konyou ni... ???
peace, chokusen made (i)kite shimatta to iu de ???
Yeah...
-Now, there's a lot of hype and interest overseas, right?
Sou iu toku ni shougyou katte iu tokoro ni kanjite ireba ???
-Ah, you're right. Indeed,
There were things I left up to hyousou??? Nicalis - to Tyrone,
-Right.
At first, I heard we'd be releasing the WiiWare in Japan too,
but when it comes to releasing it in Japan,
you need to have someone here running things,
-Yep.
-Oh, I see.
But I was a salaryman, see,
and I couldn't let this private hobby get out of hand...
-Oh.
So I thought, no choice but to give up on it.
-I see.
Right, so for overseas, you left it up to Nicalis, but...
-Right.
Domestically, izaa tte koto ni naru to???, you'd need someone here again to run things?
-That's right, I couldn't get that done, yes.
-Hmm.
Ah, from looking at Twitter, the PSP version is unofficial, as I understand it...
-Ah, that's right...
-It was ported by a volunteer, right?
-Oh, quite a few friends have played it on PSP, you see.
-Is that right?
-When I first saw it I was like, wow, it runs on the PSP! I was deeply moved.
-Right.
Although it's true that it's not official...
-Hmm.
Yeah...
The official ones are the Mac and the Wii, and the DS.
Apart from the PSP, there also seems to be a version that runs on Linux.
-Hm?
I guess that makes two of them.
Though I've never seen it.
-hontou nono??? haado de ja ima asoberun desu ne
Yes...
That's right...
There's this old hardware I haven't heard of before,
I got a mail from someone asking me to port to it.
-[chuckle]
-It's that...
What was it?
-Was it a "demake"?
-Um, let's see... Yeah, that's right.
It must have been a demake, a port to something...
Was it a Commodore?
-Ah, Commodore six four?
-Commodore sixty-four? Hehe.
Old and nostalgic hardware is super popular overseas, isn't it?
-Yeah, hardware that didn't come out in Japan...
-Yeah.
-Huh? They did come out in Japan though?
-At least the ??? did.
-Hmm...
-Lots of enthusiasts for it.
???
-Right, they don't run, do they? I haven't heard of that happening...
-Right, there's a lot of unique sound chips and such that are only growing,
I think it would be nice to see Cave Story's music remade on them.
-Hmm...
-Ah, sorry, I'm getting a little too into it there.
-No, you're right...
-Yeah...
Right, on that note, if you go on Twitter right now,
you see a lot of people going "It would be nice if it released in Japan,"
-Hm?
that's what they're saying.
-So they are. Yes, um,
I see requests like that on my BBS from time to time,
but I can't really say much beyond "I'll do my best."
-Right.
Yeah...
-Let's just check in on Niconico Live a bit...
Oh right, they're broadcasting this, aren't they?
???
-You alright? You seem out of it.
-[inaudible]
-Ah, yes.
-Oh, it's loaded?
-Yay...
Yes.
-How many people are watching right now?
-That's two... two thousand?
-...and three hundred, about?
-azuttoru kana???
-konna fuu ni zutterunda bokura???
-Oh, you're right. [waves]
-[audience laughter]
-[laughter]
demo ugotte toki masu ???
-are? ugoitehen???
-The comments all seem like tsukuri utsutsu???, don't they?
-Oh, it's lagging a bit. It was scrolling just now.
-Oh, you're right.
Yeah.
-Ah, it's back. They're waving to us from the comments.
-Yeah.
-It looks like the total number of watchers right now is about 2,300... right?
-Uhh, yes, looks like it.
Wow, the comments are... overwhelming...
-Really looks like everyone loves Cave Story, eh?
-Yes... Thank you very much, folks.
-Niconico Live toka demo ima yatteru hito kekkou imasu mon ne?
-Yes, recently there have been people making videos of themselves playing,
and considering this event could happen,
I was wondering what the players are really thinking...
-Right.
I tried watching some last week,
-Uh-huh?
but it was kinda, you know...
I made the game, so I know, but first-time players...
They don't know where to go,
-Yup.
eien tokoro roshite to mite igai dakara desu???
-[audience laughter]
[laughing]
-Gets you worked up, right? Like, "C'mon, go here!!"
-Yeah... I guess that part could be trouble, is what I think...
-Yeah.
-Yeah, when I played Cave Story for the first time,
I thought, man, if I ever meet the dev,
-[laughs]
I'd like to give him a talking-to!
Like, come on, why'd they have to make it so hard?
shou dekikai na nima iro toki kou ka na to omounde ite mimasu kowainde???
-Yes.
-[laughs]
ittai masu yo, hai???
-Yeah.
Ah, on Niconico lately, if you search for videos,
there's a lot of these "Tool Assisted Speedruns".
-Right, right, on the Time Attack...
-They use tools to achieve frighteningly fast results on the Time Attack, right?
-Yes...
toka no douga mo attari shite, himata??? chotto mori agatteru you na
-Right. Well, players recently-
Up until now, I haven't made much use of Twitter or such, but when I go and look,
it seems like there's a lot of people who know about it but haven't played yet.
-Right.
-Uh-huh.
But there's a steady increase in people thinking, "I'll play it now,"
And um...
[TL note: Windows Forest is a software download site.]
On Windows Forest, the number of downloads by now,
-Right.
-By now? Still?
seem to have reached first place, in the games section.
-Huh.
-I see.
Thank you all for your support.
-de ma koette osarai shite miru to,
overseas, there's been a lot of releases, like for the WiiWare or the 3DS,
but none domestically, despite the original developer being from here - we're lagging behind, aren't we?
-True, you're right...
-Right? It's like...
-Domestically, well...
That's right, there was the Mac version, but that's it.
-I see.
-nanka sorosoro???
-Hm?
kokunai tenkai mitai nano ga???
-Uh-huh?
-ne, nanka ??? saretemasu kedo
-[inaudible]???
-[laughs]
So, Amaya-san, will Cave Story not release in Japan?
-U-um, well...
-Like... like, oh, it's in my pocket now.
-[audience laughter]
-What?
-???
-[laughter]
-Excuse me.
-Uhh, now, there's something interesting to show you...
-Um...
-Oh?
What is it?
-It's like, an announcement, an important announcement related to the event.
-Oh, that's right, an announcement for the official site...
-Awesome. kore wa to ika ni motte??? masu yo ne
-choppa ne???
-Yeah.
-[laughter]
-Okay, let's zoom in the camera...
[laughing]
Anyways, can we see what's being revealed?
-Um, uh, first...
-Is the sound good?
-Is the ??? good?
Yep.
Oh, uh, hang on a second...
-Yes, please broadcast this.
Alright, without further ado, shall we start?
-A video, is it?
Yes, we'll be displaying it.
Well then, please enjoy.
Let's go...
-[applause]
-Whew, am I excited!
-[laughter]
-Thank you.
-[applause]
-Well? Whaddaya think?
-Yup.
-In the end there we saw Asterizm being mentioned,
-Yeah.
and that's where Nakamura-san comes in.
-Yes. Nakamura-san, if you will.
-Uhh, well, so it's like this...
the topic of a release came up at our company,
and this was brought up by Naramura, a while ago,
so I think he can tell us more about it.
-Yes.
-Uh-huh?
-So...
What kind of...
-We've been discussing with Amaya-san consistently about this for a while,
-Right.
the WiiWare, and the DSi version, we'd like to release it in Japan,
but in Japan, there's no place we can release it.
That's what the situation is like.
-I see.
So, we entered the WiiWare market too,
and tried our best, and soon, when the finish line seemed in sight,
nihon de urun??? dattara,
from their side, that is, from Nicalis' side,
-Ohh...
the overseas version, the WiiWare version, it was Nicalis who released that.
-Right.
So with that, well, for us...
it looked like we wouldn't be able to release it in Japan...
-Mhm.
So...
The WiiWare or the DSi version? - there was the issue of which one to release.
-Ah, right.
And there, since the WiiWare version's release,
-Right.
I'm talking about a year or so after that,
-Hm.
and during the revision phase, on Amaya-san's site-
-Sorry, um,
So, we had a survey put up...
-Oh, I see...
Though people wouldn't know about it, other than those visiting my site.
So anyways, after the survey was fielded,
all together, there were about 2000 emails...
-Wow, that's one heck of a pile.
-True...
mada ima demo kite kureru hito minna??? My homepage wasn't updated at the time.
-Oh.
And in there, the DSi was overwhelmingly in favour,
-Ohh...
Yes.
so it was like, okay, let's narrow the discussion to making a DSi port.
-Speaking of the DSi, well, Nintendo is launching the 3DS soon,
can it be played here?
-Oh, right. Download???
-ichiban meniitto??? kanaa to omoun desu yo ne?
-Ah, um, now that you mention it...
-Oh.
-Go ahead.
-What you were about to show earlier but didn't?
-???
-You wanted to do it a bit more Jobs-like, eh?
-Yeah, Steve Jobs, haha.
-[audience laughter]
-So anyways, speaking of which, I have this thing...
-Right, like it's in your pocket, haha!
Yes, uh so, chotto eru eru nanke???
-Right.
-C'mon, let's do this again, stand up and pull it out!
-Ok, then...
-Jobs-like?
???
-Ah, uh,
-Okay, folks, let's show some excitement. That ok?
Alright then, let's go!
-[whistling]
-[applause]
-Ah, thank you very much.
-But...
Oh, something in here...
-What is that?
Hmm,
What is it, indeed? Let's have a little look-see.
-[laughing]
-[clapping]
-[audience laughing]
Ah, sorry, haha. Uh, akanzetto???
-Right. Can we display it?
-Uh, hmm, you're right.
-Only the sound is audible?
-Hmm, it's not loading.
-Try going to the settings.
-Okay, let's see.
Hmmm...
-Yes.
Is it running?
Ok, plugged in the sound, too.
Do you hear anything?
-???
-Ah, umm, the PC-
-Yes, it's working.
-Ah, audio's working.
It was just working.
-Are you hearing this?
-Yeah.
-Well folks, until the camera is focused, just enjoy the sound.
-Hmm, alright...
-Hey, Amaya-san...
-[applause]
-So... Who's playing? May I?
Can I play?
Thanks! Alright, let's switch seats...
-Okay, I'll...
-Okay, hang on...
Uhh...
Okay, Ikeya-san, please go ahead.
-Alright, let's go! Is Story Mode fine?
-Sure.
Alright, without further ado...
We're starting at Arthur's House...
-Ah, okay, we'll see the Egg Corridor if you continue.
-Right. This is fine?
-Yeah. Well, then.
-We're starting from midway.
-Yeah.
-The LR buttons are for switching weapons, right?
-Right.
-Can we switch to the lower screen too?
-It's used for some things.
-Hmm.
-The map is displayed on the lower screen, right?
-Oh, that's right.
-Yeah.
-Ah, there it is. So that's how the screens are divided, eh?
-Yes.
You know, I'm really happy that it's running properly on the DSi, not just emulation or something.
-Is this basically a perfect port of the PC version?
-That's right, it's quite faithful to the PC version. Also,
there's something new called a Jukebox,
where if you've heard a song once, you can select it from the title screen.
-Oh.
Also, while this isn't a major change,
there's a setting you can change,
and people who found the PC version too difficult to clear
can now select "Easy Mode", and hopefully, clear the game.
-I see.
-Dialogue and such appears on the lower screen, is it?
-Right, since it's on the lower screen, it won't obscure the gameplay.
-Okay, let's keep going...
-Yeah.
-Hey, do some commentary...
-Huh?
-[laughter]
-Sorry, yeah, that would be funny. I was just playing normally.
-Yeah...
-Hmmm...
-So, what exactly changes when you adjust the difficulty?
-Oh, true, I'm curious about that.
-Difficulty adjustment? Um, well...
At first... Well, the person who was working on it,
-Hm?
ultimately, it got difficult for them to coordinate with me.
-I see.
We tried to make it as simple as possible,
and, well...
When I made Ikachan before this, I was thinking,
-Hm?
"It's no good trying to work together with me!"
-So, in the DSi version, if you start on Easy,
someone like me would be able to clear the First Cave without dying?
-Ah!
-[laughter]
-Well, dying there is almost standard, but now,
-Hmm.
uh, just once,
you'll get away with it.
-Right.
-Ah, so it's not instant death.
-It's not instant death, yes.
-Oh, is that so?
-Yes.
-ima wa ??? desuyo ne? naido rafu??? na toki dake desuyo ne?
-That's right. Um,
When you change difficulty, the protagonist's colour changes,
-Oh, the protagonist's colour is different?
-Yes. Based on a young chicken, he was coloured yellow,
-Hmm.
-Yellow, like a chick, you say?
-Yes, that's right.
-I see.
-Could you show us in detail after this?
-Oh, sure, let's look at it then.
-On the other hand, can the difficulty be increased?
-On increased difficulty, let's see,
your HP is drastically reduced, and...
there's essentially no scope to increase it.
-Oh, I see...
And the protagonist's colour, it's...
well, like a human's. Flesh-coloured.
-Oh, I see.
-Yes.
And the clothes are light blue...
-kore futsuu ni nanka sonzai masu ne???
-Oh, thank you very much.
-No plans of beating it, eh?
-???
-Uhh, so...
-Yes, that's right.
Ikeya, you're hogging all the fun, that's no fair!
-[laughter]
-[inaudible]
-Right? I want a turn too. So, please die.
-???
-"Please die", haha.
-You want me to die??
-shinde koro no kono game desu kara ne???
-[audience laughter]
-Thank you for your hard work.
-Do I see people getting up to leave?
-[audience laughter]
???
-???
-Instakill locations are important.
[chuckling]
-Instakill locations are important?
-Yes, it's designed to keep you on edge...
-Lotsa places you can die instantly, eh?
-That's right. I put one in almost every stage?
I think.
-And if you play on Easy Mode,
some of these will leave you alive?
-Ah, like this one we saw here? That's right, um...
[TL Note: Basil is not survivable even in Easy Mode. I may be misinterpreting this dialogue.]
-Oh, huh.
-You can pass through there, then?
-It's not like in Super Mario where you can fall off-screen and die,
so in place of the falling-off, I designed such instakill locations.
-Oh yeah, that's true.
-That's right, about this title screen...
-Yes, so what we see here is...
Ah, there are three save slots here,
so that's one difference from the PC version.
-I see.
-I'm going back, that ok?
-Right, is that ok?
-This, right?
-Uhh...
Story Mode
-Arthur's House
-New Game
-Jenka's House
Delete Save Data
-This one, right? The third.
-Yes.
-???
-Mhm.
???
-I see.
-Ah, no. Uh, so it's not a copy,
-No, I don't think so.
-ah de sankai, eh, mitsumete wake hodo dekimasu yo to???
-That's right.
-Well, three is more fun than one, after all.
-I see.
-The savedata in the third slot we saw earlier...
-Easy Mode
-Normal Mode
-Hard Mode
Ah, right, the protagonist's colour is different here, eh?
-Right, this is where you can select...
-This is what you were referring to, the yellow colour of a chick, right?
-Yes.
-Hmm.
...and that's Normal, and that's Hard.
-Yes, Hard.
-I'm curious about what's different in Hard Mode, exactly.
-Hard Mode, well, your starting HP is really low...
so all but surviving is pretty difficult.
Even I...
-So it's basically just low HP?
-Yeah, low HP.
It's so hard that I can't clear it myself...
-[laughter]
but really, among overseas players, and Japanese players,
there are people who've played the game with 3 HP, yes.
-Huh.
-I suppose that was in an informal self-imposed challenge?
-Right, that's right.
So there's a proper mode for such people now.
-Right.
-Story Mode
-???
-Jukebox
-Help
-So next there's this, and this?
-Ah, right.
-There's a bunch of question marks here...
...guess we'll check it out later.
-??? sou desu ne
-??? shimashouka
-Okay, let's check out the Jukebox.
-Alright.
-So here, um...
Songs that you hear in-game gather here,
and you can listen to them whenever you like.
-Ohhh.
-So once you listen to it in-game, it unlocks here?
-Yes, one by one, they're struck off...
Ah, but ???
-Right.
-I see, ???
-That's right, there's a lot.
-The icons are a little... chaotic, huh?
-You're right.
-Hmm, well, we tried making icons featuring scenes where that song generally plays...
-dou to katte arimasu yo???
-Oh, this is the title screen, isn't it.
-This?
-Yes.
-Ah.
This is the Main Theme, right?
-Yes, from the title screen.
-Ah, this is the computer...
-Yeah, it's nice.
-"Access".
-Yes.
So... I've been curious, what's this that's not yet...
-This is, um...
-It's a secret.
-Secret.
-It's a secret!
-Sorry.
-???
-Yeah.
-Over here?
-Yes.
-Yeah.
-Man, so it's really out on the DSi, huh...
-It really had us all waiting, huh.
-Yes, it's finally here...
-Yes.
-Umm,
We saw the announcement earlier about the DSi release,
so... the price is, uh, 1000 points, right?
Annou-
-1000, yes.
So... it's selling for 1000 points overseas,
but I was wondering if 1000 points would be an appropriate price for Japan.
Uhm, Nintendo cards, they start at... 1000 yen, don't they?
2000 yen, 2 or 3000 toka nande???
???
That's 1,100 points, right?
That's gonna receive backlash from users, right? kiri ga warui to???
-Hmm, I see.
de, ma sono hansen wa atte???
-Ah, I see.
???
-ama ni desu yo ne???
It's a shame. ???
-True, true.
???
-Ah, you're right.
-sou iu hassou desu ne???
-Yes.
-Also, I'm curious about "Release B"...
What is it like?
-Not yet.
Huh?
-After a few more announcements.
Not quite yet.
-I see.
-Yes.
-It's just, there's a video called "Coming Soon",
-Ok.
and right after that will be Release B.
We'd like to do a review that explains more about it.
-Okay.
-Is this "Coming Soon" video really urgent?
-I guess so...
-Uhm, so "Coming Soon" can mean various things...
-[laughter]
-And what might those be?
-Well...
-are, tsuruki kashite itadaki mashou ka?
-Alright then, let's be sensible about this "Coming Soon" business. Yes.
-???
-Haha, yeah.
Also, we got a video letter from Tyrone of Nicalis, right?
-Yeah, it's here. Hang on a minute, let's get this ready.
-Sure.
-Ah, alright.
-So, can you introduce this guy to us?
-Ah, um, so this guy is called Tyrone, and until recently...
-You mentioned this earlier, but he's the guy who
That's right.
published Cave Story overseas, right?
-It's not just Cave Story,
they keep an eye out for any interesting freeware,
and publish and advertise them to consumers.
-Ah, so it's not just Cave Story,
they've uncovered more fun games?
Yes, they find hidden gems and publish them to the public.
-Yes, they publish...
-Yes.
Uh, so the DSi, until its announcement, until its release...
???
Overseas, there's a lot of interesting DSiWare that came out,
that didn't release in Japan. And this, really...
-Ah, the video's starting.
-Oh, it worked.
This was actually only just received, wasn't it?
-Only just received, you say?
This really just came in now?
Just came in...
-Amazing timing, isn't it?
-Huh, I dunno.
This too.
This is Tyrone, Tyrone Rodriguez...
-Yes.
That's him, right?
Uhh...
ma konna shuu??? desu
Uh, he seems like a fairly good guy.
-"Fairly" good guy??
-Really good guy, I mean!
-Yes. [laughter]
-[audience laughter]
Tyrone's not around, watching, is he?
Don't wanna get yelled at!
Oh, well!
[laughter]
-Okay, are we good to play it?
-Yep, all set.
-Okay then, if you will.
-Ah, sound isn't working.
-That's so like Tyrone.
-Sorry, could you work the sound?
Aight, from the top!
-He's saying something really cool... but we can't hear him.
-Uh, not this, not this. Uhh...
Right, this one.
The sound should be fine. It's this line.
Alright, once again, let's redo this.
-Haha, let's redo this, sure.
-???
-Uh, this is a video letter from Tyrone.
-Right, right.
-[audience laughter]
So, this was just received?
-This just came in?
-It just came in!
-No sound again??
-[audience laughter]
-Aw maannn...
-Once again!
-We're trying again!
-[audience laughter]
-kore, naramura san, chotto yonde moratte ii desu ka???
-???
-yobe nain desuka???
-Different line?
-That one.
-Right.
-This PC's line?
-The camera...
...the camera...
-This thing?
-Really?
-Alright?
-Come on...
-Well, third time's the charm...
-It's working!
-Is it working?
-So, we have a video letter from Tyrone...
-[audience laughter]
-???
Oh, this here?
[audience laughter]
-[laughter]
We did it! Man, was that silly.
-Okay, let's go!
-???
-Yeah.
-Oh, and this letter just arrived!
-Yup.
-It just came?
It just came!
-Yes.
-[audience laughter]
-Let's go.
-Yup.
I am Tyrone Rodriguez, from Nicalis.
People of Japan, greetings.
I have been working with Studio Pixel since 2007,
and with Nigoro since 2008.
What sort of work, you ask?
Under Amaya-san's supervision,
I ported Cave Story to WiiWare and DSiWare,
and am working on a 3DS port.
I wonder what I should say to you people of Japan...
Hmm... Ah, that's right.
I'm real sorry it's taking so long to release it in Japan.
I would like to release the WiiWare version in Japan.
I had many thoughts, but thanks to you fans' comments, I decided to release a DSiWare version.
This way you can play it on the 3DS too.
Collaborating with the Nigoro guys, we'll be able to release it in Japan.
The land where Cave Story was born...
Japan.
[TL note: His dub says "Japan" here instead of the usual endonym "Nihon" for some reason.]
[audience laughter]
[applause]
By the way, do you want to know why Amaya-san's game has been getting attention from players worldwide?
Yes, that is because Amaya-san's latest, Cave Story, is a supremely charming game.
It is most unfortunate that I could not get to be Cave Story's developer.
???
Ah! Truly, it is wonderful.
Speaking of which, he once said:
"Having my game be released all game-like is like a dream come true."
To me, getting to work with a cool guy like Amaya-san is like a dream come true.
Honestly, I just want to jump out of this screen and reach over there right now.
Please invite me too next year.
It's all thanks to you guys, who are so darn excited about my beloved Cave Story.
I wonder who will be next to show me the best game ever?
Heheh, I'm looking forward to it.
[laughter]
-[applause]
-That was Tyrone Rodriguez.
-What was that?
-By the way, this video just came in.
-[audience laughter]
-Just came in, right? They even took care of editing in captions.
-By... the way...
There were some mistakes, right? Here and there...
-Uh, so, Japanese isn't his forte, I guess, but...
his accent was kinda funny, right?
-You're right...
ano, ??? kaigai no tsuuhan bangou mitai yatsu???
-Mhm.
That sort of thing...
I do think he was doing his best to speak well.
-Yeah.
tte koto ni shokimashou yo???
-Still, the guy who captioned it was a little evil.
-[laughter]
Must've been an intern.
Okay, but yeah, it was a great video honestly.
Thank you, Tyrone.
[applause]
Well, then. This marks the end of Part 1, doesn't it?
-Right.
-Right, so...
This has been Part 1: Cave Story Up Until Now.
I think we'll have a brief intermission, before we continue with Part 2.
Uhh, so... 10 minutes should be good, right?
-Yes.
Alright. So we'll break for 10 minutes,
right now it's... 13:10, so let us start Part 2 at... 13:20.
Uh... Ah, by the way, there's a notice.
So this is about the drinks...
Uh, it looks like the drink "Curly" has sold out.
Thank you for your patronage.
-[applause]
"Curly" really is popular, eh?
-Seems like it, huh.
-Yeah.
-Also, the results of the popularity poll will be announced later, so look forward to it.
Next, coming to food...
[TL note: According to the menu, it was samosa.]
Uh, the yellow triangular item, I'm not sure what it is,
it appears to have sold out.
Uh, there's still plenty of "Mimiga".
With that said, those who haven't tried it yet,
more should be in stock soon for you to enjoy.
-Can't level up now?
-Uhm,
-Haha, yeah, right?
-I didn't have the yellow item...
couldn't eat it, in the end.
-Amaya-san, you didn't have any?
-No...
-Aw, that's too bad...
But yeah.
So with that, let's have a short break.
Folks, please return at 13:20.
Thank you for having us.
-Thanks for sticking around.
-Thank you for having us.
-[applause]
[INTERVAL]
-Okay, it's time... Let us get started with Part 2.
I wonder where Nakamura-san went?
-Oh... he's late...
If Nakamura-san's not here, who'll handle the slides?
Nakamura-saann!
The bathroom?!
How cruel to abandon us...
Well, um, before we start,
Uhh, there's something on the whiteboard over there.
-Yes.
Oh, Nakamura-san's back.
Let's get started.
-I kinda wasn't thinking he'd come at such a time.
While we were waiting, I felt like, getting kinda restless...
-I was wondering what you were doing over there,
you were doodling away, and before I knew it, this drawing showed up.
-So instead of leaving, to relax, you just...
-Yeah...
I drew something, um,
Naramura - La-Mulana's Naramura beside me,
he wanted me to draw something...
-The guy on the left is kinda weird...
-Yeah, true, that...
-[audience laughter]
I'm betting there's a lot of people who don't recognise the characters on his head.
-It's a critter, though...
-Correct!
-That's a critter?!
-???
-That's how it is in the sprite, but...
-Yeah... If you look closely, it's like this.
if you move closer, it probably starts to look like this.
-Ahh, I see...
???
-Let's take a picture?
There were some people wanting to take pictures earlier too.
-Go ahead.
-I didn't think it'd be on display like this...
-Huh.
Yeah.
Nakamura-san, let's take a quick look at what's going on in Niconico Live.
-Yes sir. Please hold.
-It's busy in there, seems like.
-e, mou, naremashita???
-tentekomai nano ni naremashita?
-Yep.
-ka kojitsuitari???
-???
We're trending on Twitter too, thanks to you all.
Everyone's kinda flaming Tyrone's video letter, in particular.
-Yeah...
-Right, back to Niconico Live.
-Yes, Niconico Live is on screen now, and...
uhh, the live viewers are at...
...nearly 6,000 now?
-Woah, that's awesome.
Right? That's a lot more than earlier.
-Should we do introductions again?
-Ah.
-Sure.
-Hey!
[audience laughter]
-Was that even an introduction?
-"Wii, please", a commenter says...
-Well...
[laughter]
-Right? Everyone loves Balrog.
-???
-??? Oh, cool, that's interesting.
That's the thing with Niconico Live.
-Yup.
There's this call-and-response that happens over text.
-Yeah...
Right, so with that, onto Part 2.
Let us proceed.
-Yes.
-Please.
That's right, for Part 2, we'll have an additional guest, won't we?
-Yes, that's right.
The developer of Cave Story is... well,
the person who developed it is Amaya-san, but,
for various little things, um,
-Various people, uh...
-Yes.
helped me out,
during completion. And one of those people,
called Kuroihito, is...
-Right, the name Kuroihito that was in the credits,
[TL note: Kuroihito now goes by "room_909".]
-That's right.
that is, Miyazawa-san,
today - well, the camera's not pointed at him, he's over here though,
please, come up on stage.
Give him a hand, folks!
-[applause]
Yes, please come up on stage.
Come on, people, let's hear some applause!
Right.
So, for Part 2, we've invited Miyazawa-san as a guest,
to discuss how Cave Story was developed.
Well, it's in the title, isn't it?
-Yes.
"Cave Story - Behind the Scenes".
-That's right.
-Yes.
Yep. With that said,
-Thanks for having me.
from this point on, these three here will talk freely, isn't that right?
-With Amaya-san at the centre.
-Ok.
-With Amaya-san at the centre, yes.
-Um-
-So to start with...
-Yes?
[laughter]
How about you tell us about the time during which you were developing Cave Story?
-The development period, let's see...
Development time, huh...
Before completing Cave Story,
there was a one-year 'brush-up' period,
-I see.
and I was thinking of finding someone to help with debugging...
I asked about four people to help, and made a private bulletin board,
where we could post bug reports.
And over there, well, the plan was to look at a bug, fix it, and that would be that.
-Right.
But after they were called and started playing,
they started making various requests.
And so, responding to these requests... I found a year had passed.
-Miyazawa-san, were you... futori??? datta tte koto desu yo ne
-That's right.
-Yes, he lent a hand with various things, working alone.
-Yup.
-What sort of things, for example...?
-At first, bug checking mostly took the form of proofreading text.
For example, fixing punctuation marks,
-Ah, yes.
???
-There was a lot of that, gosh.
Before we knew it though, for example,
"Isn't this weapon a little too weak?",
or, say,
"If this breaks, it's definitely way too harsh"-
we slowly started raising points about stuff like that.
Uh, behind the scenes, we made use of a BBS,
[TL note: BBS = Bulletin Board System]
a BBS for the bug checkers, the staff.
The staff there consisted of... four people, right?
-Yup.
Right, you mentioned it.
-I see.
We would all talk about the beta version, exchanging mails continuously.
-That's where the final difficult stage, "Sacred Grounds", was born.
-Ah,
So it wasn't there at first?
-The route where you drain Curly Brace and all that wasn't there at first,
and in the end...
"Make an ending where you can save her", and "Make a more difficult stage"...
-Heck of a request, wasn't it?
-Yeah, no, it was fun for us to discuss this dungeon with everyone and play it,
-Yeah, we were like, "Yippee"...
And talking about it was fun, right?
-Totally.
It was fun, so I thought, "Hey, let's do this!"
So I'd go home, and when I was alone,
-[laughing]
when I was alone, I'd work on making a new stage.
-We did kind of just request it and then not elaborate...
-But after all, if it weren't for that,
making a stage like Sacred Grounds where people would be making videos of their speedruns,
y'know, thanks to that... that was the first time I found myself holding my breath so hard, I think.
-So after that, Miyazawa-san suggested making additions in the brush-up?
-Ah, yes, just him.
-On the screen right now,
-Ah, yes. Those are...
you can see a bunch of little windows...
Well, up until making Cave Story,
-Yeah?
I made a bunch of little things...
Looking at these, I'm thinking...
Um, Ikachan-
So I made Ikachan before Cave Story, right? To, um,
acquire the know-how needed for Cave Story.
-Right.
Ikachan was what you made right before Cave Story, right?
-Right, I made Ikachan all formulaic. Before Ikachan, though,
I made a program on the, uh, bottom here.
You see the flesh-coloured guy there?
-Flesh-coloured guy?
In the middle, the... brown-coloured guy?
-Hmm.
-This?
Yeah, that.
-This one?
-Yeah.
So about that... It was actually before Ikachan,
but I made him as part of "Cave Story"...
-You made him as part of Cave Story, before Ikachan?
-Right. I said earlier that Cave Story took 5 years,
but when you include this, it was more like 6 years.
-Huuuh.
So like that-
-The other day, he went rummaging through his diary.
-Yeah.
And uhh, he-
-Right, right,
I was worried I wouldn't have enough material for the event...
-He brought along an MO disc.
[TL note: MO = Magneto-Optical.]
-MO, really?
Yeah, it was like, he was desperately salvaging any data he could find...
-I see.
So...
-yoku ebou??? wo yomemashita ne
sou nan desu yo. mou kowarekake mo ???
-Well, I'd given up on that, honestly.
???
It was like, "Huh?" And before you knew it, 6 years had already passed.
-??? janai zo
-So,
You kept a diary?
-He did.
-So uh,
I started maintaining a diary around the same time I was practicing typing.
It's not at all the case today, but back then,
I'd kinda just lazily write about how that day passed,
so yeah, there was that diary, and... right, various-
-Must've made a whole lot, huh?
There were many, but pretty much none of them were really complete, you know?
Working on a game is simple enough, but bringing it to completion is where it really gets tough...
So here you can see this whole crowd of those failu- those incomplete games.
-So what sort of games were these actually? Could you give us an explanation?
-Um, well...
they're pretty short, and um,
-No like, can you actually show us?
Oh, okay. Let me see...
So if we have enough time, I could... connect it here and run it?
Umm...
-You can show us?
-Wait, you brought them all?
I have ones that run fairly well. Not all of them, though...
-So, we'll get to see the legendary Cave Story Alpha in action?
-Oh, you brought the Alpha version of Cave Story too today?
Ah, yes, I have it, but...
Well, the tempo is off, so I'm thinking, what do I do...
-The one in the middle?
-[laughter]
-It's embarrassing, I bet? Having to put it on display now, haha.
True...
-Actually, it seems like there's a lot here...
Hmm...
What's this?
???
-Ah, this,
this is, well,
something I just kinda tried making to "make something".
-This is the first thing you made, right?
I wonder where it is.
Well, no time to search, I guess, so...
-Nah, don't worry, we got time.
-We dooo?
-Part 2 of the event is a little longer.
-Okay, I'll take my time... There it is!
Oh, the screen's too small, hang on.
This first one...
chicchai no nustekurete??? iu ta nda yo kedo
-Ah, but he backed everything up in nemame???
-Unfortunately, I don't have the source...
-Ah, true, there's no source.
-This is Cave Story?
-Uhm, yes, kinda.
-This is the initial version?
-It's gotten quiet, huh.
-[laughter]
So uh, this, Cave Story,
this Cave Story that I was making in the beginning,
uh, ultimately, I...
At first, I was aiming at making a simple game,
"You're hungry, in an unknown place. How long can you survive?"
...that's the sort of game it was.
-Totally different from now, eh?
That's right... while I was making it... there were a lot of...
-Rather severe setting, innit?
You're right...
-[laughter]
-What is the character doing in this place?
-Well, the map is kind of formless right now, in the development stage,
-Uh-huh...
-and I remade it after that, something that runs a little better...
Hmm... was it here? I hope this runs alright.
Let me get this ready - oh it already is.
Hmm...
The screen is a bit small, but...
This was just about picking up fruits, which was kind of boring, so...
The protagonist here looks kind of like the protagonist from Cave Story, right?
-Yeah, he's wearing a cap.
-Yes, the cap. Although it's blue here...
So that's the sort of game this became.
And at this point, well, I gave it up.
-At this point?
Because the program was a huge sticky mess by now.
Any developers in the audience probably know this, but...
If you head into development without a plan, it slowly but surely gets all messed up, yeah...
Anyways, what I made after this was Ikachan.
And making Ikachan-
-I see. So before Ikachan, you made these, uh,
-Yes.
these projects that never saw the light of day, as practice for Cave Story.
-The things we just looked at.
-And after finishing Ikachan, I started this-
[loud music]
-Woah.
-Wow, that's loud.
Volume control here...
-Uh-huh.
-Let me just reduce the volume, let's see...
-About 50% should be good.
Hmm...
Man, this is kind of a pain...
-Ikachan was distributed, though. A lot of people know about it, right?
-Yes, I released it...
But there's a lot of people who only know Cave Story.
-Anyone who's played Ikachan here? Raise your hands.
-Ah.
-Woah.
-They've all played it, nice.
-You're right.
-What's cool is, there's a grade-schooler over there,
-Thank you for playing it.
who raised their hand as hard as they could, like they thought "Yes!" and wanted to show it. Awesome.
-Anyways, I remade this after that, and...
-This looks a bit more... game-ish, eh?
-You're right, though there's still a little friction in there...
-There's BGM too, now.
Yeah, the BGM here is something I developed, called Piyopiyo...
-Hmm.
-Organya wasn't a thing yet?
-That's right. Um,
-I believe this was, like, developed with Ikachan in mind.
-Yeah.
-Ah.
-I see.
-It was at that stage here.
-For the background music,
system wa pisu??? no mono wo tsukatteru n desu kedo
Ah, but well,
it wasn't that good, so I redid it.
After redoing that...
It was from this point that Cave Story took 5 years.
-Ah, 5 years counting from there?
What about what we just saw?
-That was one year. Then I made Ikachan and the thing we saw earlier...
The Alpha version doesn't count?
-Huuhhh...
-Well, he was hospitalised twice in that time.
-[laughter]
-Is that so?
-Hospitalised twice, right...
-Ikachan was actually developed while he was in the hospital.
-That is correct.
-First he had... was it pneumonia?
-Umm, they uh, they said it was tuberculosis...
-Ah, kekkaku wasaki??? ka
-I was under quarantine.
-Oh my...
-No visitors, either.
-Oh.
-Ah.
-This is...
-It's Cave Story!
-You can recognise Cave Story now.
Or at least, the Cave Story that I then remade...
-The Beta version, right?
-Yeah, this is called the "Beta version"...
DIM PATH
-Right.
So here I had a money-based system,
so with this, um...
By managing your money, you could buy weapons.
-Ohh.
And uh,
The ammo is limited, as you can see.
-Oh, you're right.
-The thing on top?
-That's right.
-that reads 37?
-Yes, 37.
The upper-left is ammo, and the lower-left is money, right?
-Correct. If you have 37 bullets, then, well...
they disappear in no time. So you have to economise...
PUU'S RESTAURANT
That's the basic problem here...
OPENED THE TREASURE CHEST.
GOT 100 CION.
HEY THERE.
WELCOME TO PUU'S RESTAURANT.
"Hey there." Should be here soon...
-Ah!
-Huh?
-This is, well,
WELL NOW, TODAY'S MENU IS...
-Huh, looks different.
-It's Balrog's predecessor.
-Yes, that's...
-4? What's 4 mean?
Huh? 4? Where?
Oh, there, haha.
I'd added serial numbers to keep track of the face graphics.
HUH, YOU'RE NOT A MIMIGA?
THEN, DO YOU WANNA BE BUBBLE FRIENDS WITH ME?
AIN'T NO WAY THAT'S HAPPENING.
PUU KNOWS YOU.
YOU CAME HERE TO KILL ME, DIDNT'CHA?
-Oh, he doesn't just look like that?
-That's right,
I forgot to erase it in the end...
-He's not version 4 or something?
-Ah, no, he isn't.
At this point, Balrog-
-mou daibu ???
Ah, yes.
-This is Balrog, right?
-He's called "Puu", he came before Balrog.
-Huh.
-Woops, no ammo left.
-What now?
-Yeah, what do you do if you run out of ammo?
-If your ammo runs out...
Oh, I still had some more.
Now I can beat-
-[laughter]
-[audience laughter]
CONTINUE? YES/NO
-Aww...
Well, that's what kind of game this was.
-I see.
So this, I uh...
Well, this took two years,
-Hmm.
and I was almost finished,
but uh...
Now, I hadn't shown this to many people yet, only a few close friends,
and they had good things to say about it, pretty much,
however, uhh...
There was this person called Nao who had taught me programming,
-"Nao"-san?
-Yes.
-Ok.
And he had some really severe criticism for me.
Um...
After showing it to him, I lost all self-confidence.
-[laughter]
He-
-He really criticised it, huh?
-Oh, boy, he criticised it, he lambasted it to no end.
After that, I showed it to some other friends,
and they had mostly unfavourable reviews,
One day when he'd come over to hang out, I had him play the game.
Going further, there were all sorts of problems I kept trying to plug up,
-I see.
and in the end I just redid the whole thing.
-So what exactly were the problems?
Well, let's see...
In the end...
For starters, they said it was hard to figure out.
Looking at the gameplay from earlier, uh...
When the player was lost, you wouldn't know where to go, and end up wandering in circles...
mo kyukutaa??? ni iu to sore no katamari nan desu ne
There was this constant feeling of "I don't know what to do now".
-Right, in the old version, when you went through the door in the first cave,
you found yourself in the Plantation already.
-That's right, the Plantation used to be an initial stage.
-???
-Yeah...
It was big, and you couldn't tell where to go.
-Now that you mention it, yes, it was big and easy to get lost in.
-Earlier, you died in that boss fight, right?
-Yeah, so if that happens-
-If you're out of ammo, how do you survive?
-Ah, if you're out, well, you just die.
-[laughter]
There wasn't any scope for rescue...
-Huuhhh...
-Pretty harsh, eh.
-Yeah.
It is...
-So if you're forced into a situation like that...
-Yes, um, I wanted to do something about it, but...
-Normally, if someone's developing a free game, then to that extent...
like, to say, "Change it all from the ground up!"...
-Well,
-Well, since it's free, you also have to rely on others, right?
Like, "it's free, so you don't need to work that hard..."
-It would be more normal to just give up, I'd say.
Like, "This ain't happening!"
-Ahaha.
-You have a point.
Well, you know, while I was working on something,
I'd just be thinking, man, I wanna start making the next game soon.
So then I'd start hurrying it up,
hanashi nashuu ???
-Ah, you'd start dreaming about your next work.
-Well, um, the weapon system and all, the game's problematic part,
it made me want to redo it,
Um,
I'd been troubled for awhile, like, "What do I do about this?"
And finally concluded that there was no choice but to start again from the top.
-This remaking business is described on Wikipedia and such, isn't it.
-Ah, you're right.
-And the restarted development took a year, basically?
-Yeah, from there, it was a year of
remaking, and then a year of brush-up.
-Hmm.
-That's right.
With something or another coming up, it took about 3 years before I could rest.
-So Nao-san, on whose advice you restarted development...
Did you show him your progress when working on the new version?
-Yeah, about that...
I didn't show him!
I was scared.
-Yeah...
-Because of the criticism the first time?
-Right. I was scared, so I didn't show it to him.
When the game was finished, at that time, um,
I really just wanted to go "Woohoo! All done!"
But right after, I had to follow through more than I'd thought,
chasing bugfix after bugfix...
I was like, enough, I just want to get away from this game already!
It was really chipping away at my nerves...
-Was it listening to Nao-san's criticism
that led to the brushing-up?
-Right, right. So, he was...
He was the key person, so to speak.
-I see.
-Nao-san is here in the audience, right?
-Yes.
-I wonder if he can share what sort of commentary he had...
The wireless mike, Nao-san has it right now, right?
-He has it, yeah.
-Right.
-Good.
-Then, Nao-san, well... the camera isn't focused toward you,
but from the audience, please share a few words.
-Just the voice...
-Don't try and look for him, ya hear?
-[laughter]
-Don't look for him, you say? Sure.
So, Nao-san, can you tell us about what sort of advice,
...err, criticism, you had to share at that time?
-[laughter]
-If you would please.
-The gist of it, like Amaya-kun mentioned earlier,
well,
The weapon system, and not knowing where to go next,
if these major- it wasn't stimulating, so...
if these problems were resolved, that'd be nice, is what I said.
And...
The game he made earlier, Ikachan, was compact,
-Hmm.
-Yeah.
It was cohesive and well-arranged,
so when [Cave Story Beta] came out, it was a bit different from what I was expecting.
-It was flimsy, wasn't it?
-Yeah...
-Flimsy?
-So uh... in Ikachan's time,
the era of gaming was brief ???, so that was fine, but...
this time I was close to thinking, the scope of this game is really big, it'll be impossible to manage.
-Hmm.
So yeah...
-Yes... Also,
while the action was fun, the same way as in today's Cave Story,
tama wo bari bari uttete kyotao??? sou to omottara, ano
okane de kawanai teki nai de mottainakute tama ga utenai???
-Yeah,
doushite mo ano okane no system wo irenakute???
sutto iu kota o mise ga hoshii to. tte o mise ni hinpai ni kite morau ni wa, ???
buki no tamakazu wo seigen shinai to ikenakunatte
-Ahh, I see.
And, when you run out of ammo, like in the boss fight earlier,
you may have money left, but you can't find a shop...
It's supposed to be an action game,
but there are spots like that where the tempo is ruined.
Oh, also,
The free version didn't jou gei uchi???
-Ohh, I see.
I actually wanted to be able to
shoot downward when in midair,
but shooting vertically wasn't
implemented in old Cave Story.
Um, there was a puzzle-based stage,
PAZARU TEKI NA SUTEEJI
-Oh yeah?
where you have to figure out how, what sequence,
to break blocks in to be able to proceed...
So that didn't work out.
-I see, so it got to where you had to rework it entirely.
-That's right...
-Ah, but wait, with the adoption of the money system, off the bat,
-Right.
it makes sense to feel strongly about it one way or the other. ???
-Hmm...
Although, you would be quite curious about what you can buy there.
-Uh...
maa iwareta toki wa soko made dekinee yo to wa iu ndesu kedo ???
-I suppose so.
??? demo jissai mada hitori de program wo shiteru to sono
sono scene wo tooru tabi??? iwareta koto omoidashite
-During development?
Right, during development, like eugh... gotta redo this after all... But it did get better!
When I got rid of limitations on weapons and made them all unlimited ammo...
It was hella fun.
-[laughter]
But in the end - in the end -
-masa niima??? no doukutsu monogatari no sugata desu yo ne
-You're right. Uhm...
Yeah, I thought there would be a thrill when you run out of mon- I mean, ammo,
but instead of thrill, it was more like stress.
-I see.
-iu koto ni higasuite???, yeah...
-In the final version, you have missiles that saabisu suru??? boss fights, right?
-Right.
Was this in reaction to that?
-Aww, man... I guess I forgot and left that in!
-Was that a remnant of the old system?
-Yeah?
-Hmm... I guess, yeah, when it came to the missiles... you're right.
Hmm...
kekkyoku sou desu ne ano nanka tii??? ga nanka baramaite
??? sore wo hirou no wa doushite mo iratakatte
sore ga energy capsule toka iu no de
Right,
The 'Yellow Item' in today's menu, that's its name.
-Is that the official name? 'Energy Capsule'?
-Well, it's like, energy for your weapon, so...
-So it's not an official name?
-It's... Not an official name.
-Wait, it's not?
-Yeah...
-They don't look like capsules though, huh?
-Hmm, you're right...
-They're triangle-shaped.
-They look like triangles.
-They're triangles.
-???
-Uhh... 4-sided dice?
-4-sided dice, right.
-Or what we call a "d4".
-Is that so?
-You guys get what I'm saying, right?
-Not really...
-Oh you do, thanks guys.
-???
-TTRPG players in the audience, I see.
-Today... You're right,
If you look around, there's a lot of young people, which is kind of surprising.
-You're right.
Cave Story was originally meant to be, nostalgic,
to people who'd played on the Famicom,
[TL note: Known outside of Japan as the NES.]
or old things like that,
-Hmm.
But it coming out on WiiWare and such,
that's only been possible because there are so many younger players,
so thank you for your support.
-Yeah, the popularity on Niconico Douga,
I wonder if that's what caused the word to spread.
-Ah, I see...
-When I tried playing it,
-Yeah?
It was... easy to play.
-I see.
-Yeah.
-You're right.
-The jumping movement feels good,
and there's no lag when attacking.
-Uh-huh.
The difficult mechanics you mentioned earlier were excised,
-Right.
leaving behind a simple, easy-to-play system.
And you get to enjoy these elements right away.
There were many such parts in the game, I feel.
-No matter what, when developing, you feel like, "I wanna do this and I wanna do that too,"
-You're so right. Like,
-Also, a big obstacle is when you think,
"I wanna make a game that's totally novel."
-Oh, yeah.
With Cave Story, there weren't any particularly new mechanics,
it's a lot like games that are already around.
I just tried making a game like that in my own way.
dakara tsukutteru toki, kansei ssu no kondake ga attandesuyo yappari ano
tsukutteru aida ni, nitai you na game wo dareka ga dasun janai ka tte iu no wa,
kekkou bikurishite tsukuttetan desu yo ???
-But anyways, you had really been rushing, right?
-Like, "I wanna release this quick."
-I was in a hurry, yeah.
A lot of times I considered releasing an incomplete version, thinking, "I really wanna show this off!"
With the way I only did one final release,
It really sapped my motivation during development,
-Yeah.
because I really wanted to show it off.
sore mo kekkou tsurae ??? toki
-So...
It took like, 5 or 6 years for development, right?
Being able to say, "I did it!",
the finish line just out of reach,
sitting at your computer the whole time, clacking away at the keyboard,
-Oh, yeah.
thinking, what am I even doing?
-[laughter]
-Yeah so uh...
The brush-up was actually pretty fun,
Up until then I'd been alone, working in silence...
Now, during [brush-up], there were various prob-
Err...
A lot of requests I heard out, I guess.
-And you passed?
-I passed, yeah, a lot of feedback went back and forth.
-Well, Cave Story wouldn't be what it is, if not for this process, right?
-Yeah.
-Now, the weapon level system was brought up earlier...
-Right.
This wasn't in the previous version, right?
-No, it wasn't...
-Was implementing this also a part of Nao-san's advice?
-That was, well... uh,
The idea of picking something up to improve your weapons,
-Right.
I got rid of money, so in its place...
-You wanted something else to pick up?
-You're right, I wanted something for players to pick up.
This would motivate them to actually kill enemies, so yeah...
That's how it was. I think it worked out almost miraculously well...
-I see.
-[laughter]
-jaa nerattetatte yori wa tsukutte mita kekka yokatta tte iu kanji nandesu ne
-You're right. Um,
On the whole, in the game,
you have to think while moving,
so if you don't have a strategy, you can't implement the tactics.
-That makes sense.
-There's no worldbuilding either.
-Right.
-nanka itsumo ichimai e mitai nano kaite, de soko kara
kore wo doushitara game ni naru ka tte ??? douyatte koto ga ooin desu yo
-Ah, right...
-Hmm...
-So, back in the day, I would get magazines of the Famicom and such,
and they would include lots of screenshots of games.
-[laughter]
-Mhm.
And restricted to looking at the screenshots, I thought it was super cool.
And I thought, man, I really wanna try this! And when I did,
I found it wasn't like what I'd thought. You know, like with film trailers.
-Right.
So, when looking at those screenshots,
the impressions I had - if I could give them shape, I could make something interesting, I thought.
-So, even if it's relatively small, "I want a game like this", or "it would be nice to have a game like this"...
-maa arui wa deshou ne ano
-tama tte tte katachi ???
-So...
-senzaiteki ni doushite mo
-Seeing that version of Cave Story earlier made me think...
That airy quality of the jumping movement hasn't changed, has it?
-Oh, you're right. About that,
-About that,
did you feel like the jumping was already perfected by that point?
-Ah, you're right, I suppose...
Well, this might be a bit of a technical discussion, but.
???
Like, how much gravity do I set to make the player move like this?
While moving, too, there's minor adjustments going on, right?
I want to climb this part, but I can't -
how do I achieve that height?
I had made these decisions in the beginning,
so it just remained like that the whole time.
-Huh...
-The jump feels quite airy, were you particular about this?
-Well, I was wondering how much should you be able to
adjust your trajectory mid-air, and various stuff like that...
But stuff I've played so far, they're rather,
influenced by the vibe and tone of other games, I guess.
-So in the beginning, the jump you implemented,
it was basically through trial-and-error, right?
-You're right...
-But you know, he, uh...
He was fussing over the details,
and ended up happy with how it turned out.
Once while we were talking, he brought up
the topic of the jump in Super Mario,
-I see.
and your trajectory when you collide with a pipe-
-Ah yes, that.
He really liked that.
-[laughter]
-donna koto itenasu??? ka
-Yeah, from the start, I thought Super Mario had really good movement...
-Yeah, yeah.
But I suppose no one actually jumps like that, though...
-Sorry,
-Ah, sorry, let's hear the details. What exactly...?
-So, the pipes look... like this, right?
So... When you jump towards the pipe,
-When you jump...
and just as you start to ascend, you collide with it,
sono toki ni, dou iu tsugi kyourou??? suru ka
-Ah,
-Hmm.
How about we draw it out...
-Oh, on the board? Ah, yes, please go ahead.
-Let's see...
-Gee, this might've become a bit of a bother...
-Well, uh...
Not sure if I can make my point in this space,
but let's say this is our pipe,
and when we jump,
well, if you can't alter your trajectory mid-jump,
...this is what it ends up like, right?
-Mm, yeah, it does.
So after this, no matter what you do,
when you hit a pipe you know your trajectory will go like this,
-Mhm.
and you want to be able to, uh, right yourself...
-After that, ??? Yeah.
"It would be helpful to control my movement midair!"
Is what you think.
Now, if you consider the laws of physics, moving like that in midair...
-Isn't possible, yes. Generally,
-Isn't possible.
when thinking of making a game,
you wish you have flashes of insight like this...
-nanka sou iu tokoro o
jibun de ???. He's been like that since his student days.
-Ohh I see.
He's been making games since he was a student, right?
-That's right.
-Well, uh, I learnt programming from Nao, who I mentioned earlier,
and, with that as my impetus, started making games-
-Wait,
How old were you at this time?
-I was a teenager, I think uhh...
-19, right?
-[inaudible]???
-Oh? Rather late, innit?
-It is late, yeah. I didn't have a PC at home either...
-Mhm.
-Well, Cave Story's initial, uh, Alpha version,
that was like, the 2nd or 3rd thing he made on his own from scratch.
-Ah.
So bit by bit, as he figured out what he could program,
-Yes, exactly.
he got around to games?
-Well, at that time, I was like, I would love to be able to make a game like this...
I really like action games after all, yeah...
-Right, action games...
Apart from that I've made shooting games and stuff too, but, uh...
I'm kind of busy, so with what little time I have,
it's like, hmm, how much of this game can I make?
Though I don't like shooters as much.
-I see.
So you've made shooters too, huh?
-Right, I have... It's called Guxt,
and it's a game made on really low resolution, but...
-Oh, did you bring that too, today?
What's this... oh, a rebuild...
Hmm... Looks like I moved it...
-Guxt, though, it's a pretty long game you made, eh?
-Ah well, I started making a small shooting game,
and it took...
a year, yeah, one year.
-At first,
there was a fullscreen version thing too, right?
-Ahh... That's...
A much older thing...
But you know, some of the face graphics from that... have remained-
-The eyeball characters.
-Yes, all the characters in Guxt are eyeball-based...
Hmm, where was this...
Shooting game, right... STG...
Don't think I brought it.
-Shall we move on then?
-Yes, please.
-So to start with, was there any particular event,
that made you think, "I want to start making games"?
-Well, I've always really wanted to make games, but...
Um,
I had no idea how to make them.
I didn't even know the word "programming".
Later, when I was in my senior year of high school, um...
I was...
I was really into game music,
-Hmm.
and I'd record music on a keyboard,
[TL note: 'uchikomi' means either 'step recording (in electronic music)', or 'putting one's heart into'. Both meanings fit here; was it a pun?]
imagining that I'm making music for my own game,
PCM wo tsukuttare ???
-So you started with the music, and imagined the game from there?
-That's right. With Cave Story, too, uh,
in the case of Cave Story,
it was the music that was developed first.
Um...
-The music first?
-Yes... I conceived the rest of the game following the soundtrack.
-Right, the song we heard earlier, Cave Story followed from that, no?
-Yes, right, uh...
That's right, um,
that thing from before Ikachan,
its title screen music was called 'Cave Story',
not this, I think...
-Was it this?
-Uhmm... That's right!
-All these are sound production programs, right?
-Yes. Uh...
-???
-Mus-
Err, yes, that's right...
When I first thought about making a game soundtrack,
generally, on the PC, you had MIDI.
-Right.
I uh, had originally recorded sampled audio with PCM,
but I wanted to distribute the finished game to people, right?
But then I ran into a problem of volume-
WAV files were much too heavy.
MP3 wasn't a thing yet, at least, it wasn't common.
-Right.
So I thought I'd do my soundtrack in MIDI,
but back then there were a lot of people who didn't have MIDI,
-Yeah,
-I get you.
-So - You get it?
That was around 2000...
-There's lots of soundfonts you can have in MIDI,
that all sound different, right?
-Yeah, you can have a virtual sound source, but that's...
It's really heavy, so...
It won't do for a game.
ano koukau??? no narashi kata wa wakatta to
sore de doremiya sorashido wo koukan wo dzushite irete???
So then, um...
"kiyoku tsukureba ii jan" tte iu tokoro ga hajimattan desu yo ne
-Ooh, I see.
-motomoto koukau??? no system ni, onkai wo noseta mitai na kanji?
-That's right,
Um...
That's what I started with at first,
and um...
I started from there,
and once I learnt a bit about waveforms,
hakei-teki kiyoku speaker ga dou zengu suru ka dake
tte iu koto ni kigatsuitara,
sugoi omoshiroku natte,
-Mhm.
so I made a software where you can fiddle with the waveforms.
-You started with something fiddly?
-Yeah, haha.
-Yeah, that's right.
-So before I restarted Cave Story,
when I wanted to make the next thing,
that is, Organya's successor, namely Pxtone Collage,
-Uh-huh.
...I didn't bring it today, but it...
It was a handful.
-Um...
program wa nan nin ka to tsukiae arun desukedo
-Right.
This sound program, if it just runs within the game, that's good enough.
So by holding back on its construction, you can make it quickly,
-Yeah...
-Just include only the necessary parts for playback,
and you can get away with, well, a simple program.
So... Why bother with all the frilly graphics...?
-[laughing]
-All the cute animals and stuff...
-Hmm, you have a point.
-You're right. So uh, the thing up here, called PiyoPiyo,
I drew all these superfluous fishes and stuff,
-This one is PiyoPiyo, right?
-Like these here...
-This one? I see.
-Yeah, this is PiyoPiyo.
So for the Ikachan soundtrack, I made- er, I used this engine.
-So about when did you start to draw?
-Ah, drawing, um...
Well, I've been drawing since long ago,
but I never really studied or learnt to do it properly...
Wait, so...
The programming came last?
-Yes.
-Ohh...
-That's right.
-Yeah...
-Bit unusual, no?
-Pretty unusual I think, yeah.
-You know, uh...
-Were you also self-taught in music?
-As for music, well, I had an Electone, which I took a few lessons for.
Electone is that thing by Yamaha...
[TL note: Electones are a line of electronic organs produced by Yamaha.]
-Yeah.
With an Electone, your left hand constantly presses down on ???,
and the harmony is played automatically...
-Yeah, yeah...
So from there I picked up on how that's done.
-I see...
-Yeah, that's it.
After that, adding melodies on top,
I tried it out, just kind of starting somewhere...
So yeah...
-Um, just to add onto that a bit, but uh...
In those days, kono "CS" tte iu mono desu to ka
sono mae ni deteta game wo korotte??? no wa
they weren't released on the internet like they are now,
-Yep, yep.
You had these things called floppy discs. Um,
-Oh, yeah.
-Oh, are there people who've heard of floppy disks here in the audience...?
-Looks like it!
-But we don't have floppies any more, right?
-But floppy disks aren't really around any longer, right?
-naishi datte ne
I think 3.5" ???
-???
-But the 8", man, used it a lot.
-Ah, I know the 8".
-Oh, someone understands. I'm so glad!
-But yeah, despite compression, it couldn't fit under 1.44 MB.
So, ruling out WAV and MIDI,
he thought, "Okay, I'll make my own thing to solve this problem!",
And thus, PiyoPiyo was born.
-...so I made PiyoPiyo.
-Yep. So Cave Story as it is now,
the file size is very, very tiny - as I'm sure you've all noticed,
are mada zutto floppy wa, kare ga hikitsutterun desu yo???
-Downloading it from the internet, though,
-File size on a floppy...
this was an era where any number of megabytes seemed like too much.
Back then,
-sonna hayai kaisen ???
-Right, well,
Trying to download 1 MB would make you go insane.
That's the kind of era it was.
-By the way, how heavy is the final version of Cave Story?
-Hmm, I'm not sure what it is after decompression,
but the compressed file is 1 MB...
-It's really tiny.
-You can say that again.
-Yeah...
-But yeah, to get a smaller filesize,
I used the assembler to optimise and really squeeze it like an obsessed weirdo.
-[laughter]
Managed to shave off several hundred kB that way.
-Mhmm.
That's as far as I got, though...
-Hmm, but the small filesize is also good for the DSiWare release and such, right?
-Ah,
That's right, um...
There's the problem of the console specifications,
but definitely, if it was made to run well on PC,
then porting it to DSi won't pose any problems, yeah.
-Now this might be a slightly delicate matter, but Naramura-san's La-Mulana,
-Yes?
-Yep.
when porting it to WiiWare, filesize was a big concern, right?
-shiruka to omoimashita yo ne???
-That blog post was quite something.
-So in our case, at first,
we didn't really...
...think about the restrictions too much, and just kept developing freely.
When the constraints hit, we found we couldn't fit the graphics, the sound...
So, one by one, we had to shave things off,
trying to fit things into a 32-bit machine,
going back to how development was in the old days.
-Right...
-??? chotto dassen shimasu kedo
-Are there... many people here, who know La-Mulana...?
-Oh, yeah.
-Looks like quite a few!
-'Preciate it.
-[laughter]
-Oh,
-Thank you.
-[belly laughter]
Ah, right, that was Sameer-san, from a certain program. (???)
He's here, but he's hiding.
-Yeah...
-Right, so... Organya, we were able to implement that on the DSi fairly straightfowardly,
-Huh, I see.
-Considering the DSi port,
well, it was quite close to Cave Story's PC version.
-Mhmm.
-So uh, actually using tools like these...
-Right.
making the music in this,
how does it work actually, like,
could we have a look at the data?
-Data? Right, hmm...
Ok... Let's get the screen over here...
Ah.
kande karen da na???
-So I'm pretty sure that the Organya files
from Cave Story have been made public, right?
-Yes, they have.
Uhm...
Sorry about this...
Hmm...
Where was it...
Cave Story's...
Should be ORG, is this it...?
-Ah, lots of .org files here.
-Yep, this is it.
-Ah, the Organya you made for Cave Story?
-Yes, this is Organya.
-So this is actually, what we see here on-screen is what you used to make the soundtrack.
-That's right. Um...
I can't seem to get it in fullscreen.
This isn't fine art, I just kinda brute-forced notes that sound good...
-Ohh.
-How do you edit the data in this?
-Alright, new file...
-Hmm, I'd like to see that, yeah.
-Let's go...
-Here goes...
-Huh? Click?
-Yep, you click.
And if you click again, the note is extended.
-I see.
-Ah, it gets longer depending on how many times it was clicked.
-Right.
-Hang on a sec. This is how you made all the songs in Cave Story?
-Correct. Placing one note at a time like this...
-[laughter]
-That's right, he didn't use a MIDI interface.
-Though it could be said that's the natural way to do it...
-Yeah...
-No keyboard input, it seems.
All mouse.
-Doing this is fine-
-Wait, this is how you did it?
-Ah, but well, when you look at it, it's like, Of course you can do it this way.
Like an "Oh, I see", kinda feeling.
-Ooohh, it's real!
-Just playing it by ear, you know?
-Ah, but once you get used to it, it seems easy to use.
-Yeah... Ah, but after making Organya,
I made something called Pxtone Collage,
-Right.
and what was my motivation for that? Well,
there were a lot of people using Organya,
and making music with it.
-Oh, people using Organya?
-Well, it's a tool I released publicly...
So there were a lot of people using it...
So I felt like my homepage wasn't getting enough activity...
-Right.
-I see...
Yeah, so...
I made [Pxtone], yeah.
-There are actually quite a few songs made in Organya that you can see uploaded on NND, right?
-Yeah, and Pxtone Collage too.
-I see.
-Yeah... That's how it is...
-So uh... What exactly is Pxtone Collage?
-You wanna take a look at it?
-I wanna see it.
-Yes, please.
-Okay, then...
Where- which should I search...
Uhh...
Hmm.
-Could you explain the differences between each of these composing softwares?
-So in PiyoPiyo,
oto narasu tte iu shinmo??? shikanakatta ndesu yo
-Hmm.
So...
-This is a bit-
-Maybe later, haha.
-It is a bit much if you're not used to it...
Ok, uh,
Hang on a moment, ok then...
...And play...
-Hmm.
Ah, the audio is, uh... the audio's not working.
-It was just working with Organya, wasn't it?
-Ah.
Ah, it's working.
So, this was made by a certain JAP-san,
-I see.
who regularly composes music, using Pxtone Collage.
So, at first, with PiyoPiyo, used in Ikachan,
notes would play without stopping.
Then in Organya, you could start a note and then stop it.
And now, with Pxtone Collage,
you can record your own samples, and use them to make anything.
-Woahh.
-Coool.
-You can stack waveforms?
-Yes.
-Can you also import WAV files?
-Yes. About that,
you know, there are a lot of people who are
composing full-fledged, professional songs using their own samples.
Also, uh...
The last on this list,
there's a link to a talk page that I want to see again,
there's some amazing songs.
-I see.
-By the way, I think this is that person who made an album, right?
-Ooh...
A foreigner.
-Yes, a foreigner again...
Right, until today I'd been asking them to send something, I'm glad I got approval.
korenchuu de ???
-Ah, we're doing the same thing,
even now, when producing using a game device, we prepare the waveforms ourselves.
-Right.
de onkai wo, file tsukutte
-Ah, true.
kara sore kinenbi ni??? kanatteru to omoimasu yo
-Yes, yes.
-Yes, changing the frequency to make different notes, right?
Yeah...
-Hm, If you use a chip's sound source,
it completes the work, and it sounds nice too.
-True. Someone who likes this sort of sound is...
-Ah, yes.
-I like it a lot.
-On the other hand, while I've tinkered with MIDI sound sources,
something like a piano or guitar...
-Yeah?
samples that you'd have a word for,
I'm not good with instruments, so I don't have a sense for analysing them.
-Oh, I see.
When I set out to make something like that,
um,
sou iu oto dake de tsukureru ??? nante kara kyouzuki tanoshikunattanda
-Uh-huh.
-So I have a quick question,
The sound,
-Yes?
you did that, then started drawing as a hobby,
-Yes.
and then started programming at 19?
But before that point, had you never felt like wanting to make a game?
You know, generally...
Before RPG Maker was a thing,
-Uh-huh?
there was something called Dante.
-Oh, yeah.
-Right...
But you know, in the countryside back then,
no one had a PC, except this one friend.
-Hmm.
And he was like, let's make an RPG!
so he said, and taught me...
I used to hang out at his place,
-In this dude's house?
-Yeah.
[laughter]
But you know, the game never got done in the end.
There was a bit of dialogue,
-Just got it running and started?
-and that was it - Yeah.
We started with graphics, right? Pixel art,
-Hmm.
we'd keep using really saturated reds and yellows,
-Yeah...
and ended up making nothing but rather unrealistic characters.
But speaking of the history of pixel art,
That's right, the uh...
We couldn't just up and buy a Famicom,
-Yes, yes, yes, yes, yes!
and keep it at home, but you still like games,
-Yeah.
so you'd get yourself some graph paper,
-Yeah... and look through the magazines...
-Oh my gosh, yes, all the time.
and fill colours in that...
-You haven't done that?
-Oh, I have.
-Ah, so you have.
-So...
Before I actually said I want a Famicom,
my parents got me something else.
-And what was that?
-It was the MSX.
-Ah.
-Oh, haha.
And my pocket money was never enough, somehow.
-Haha.
game katte morae no wa meni ikkai katte???
demo sore wa mou, baka na you ni nari komushi ???
-Well, because we weren't allowed to buy it, ironically,
we rebelled by becoming like this, getting deep into gaming...
-Yeah,
-[laughter]
-We survived a drought!
-Even if we didn't have a Famicom,
we wielded the effect of a Famicom.
-Yep.
-Mm.
Duck through this door, open the map, pew-pew!
-Oh, yes, yes, yes.
-Playing the music in your head.
-Exactly.
-An Air Famicom, if you will.
-Yeah.
-An Air Famicom, hah.
Yeah...
-Wait, when's the last time you actually used a Famicom?
-Ah, I finally bought one recently.
-Recently?!
-You did not need to do that, man.
-I couldn't find a Famicom,
-Right.
so, uh, I got a New Famicom.
-I see.
-So you really never played it in its time?
-I didn't, no...
So yeah...
-Cave Story has a bit of a Famicom feel to it...
-Ah, yes, it does.
So, that wasn't based on the real thing?
-So... When I was making it,
I thought it would never get done unless done in that style.
That's what I thought, but when I set out to work on it,
I found myself saying, this isn't good enough, that won't do...
Like when you're writing on a blackboard and you slowly end up drifting towards the upper-right...
-That's a funny example.
-demo akogare wo attan janai no kana?
-akogare wa...
hako nitai suru akogareta no wa, definitely
-???
even now, kinda, a little bit remains, no?
-Yeah, yeah.
-Development borne out of Air Famicom hardship?
-Ah, yes, haha.
-The image of a Famicom you had in your head,
-konna machine ichiban dai???
-Yes, yes.
-is what came out.
-was given form, eh?
-Yes.
-This thing's specs are a bit more than the Famicom's, right?
-Well,
-Oh, they're a lot more.
-Like specs for the ideal Famicom?
-I'd probably know if I programmed for the Super Famicom,
but I think it's impossible.
-Ohh.
The memory just isn't enough.
-I see.
-Ah yeah, there's a lot of kyarasuu??? and stuff.
-Yeah...
-A lot of big maps need to be loaded, right?
-Right, in the Famicom era,
enemies that didn't appear on-screen didn't move,
-I see.
you could effectively pretend they didn't exist.
-Right.
But in Cave Story, no matter how big the map is,
everything is always walking around...
-Huh...
Super Famicom de mo tabun muzukashii geitoyatobun??? des yo ne...
-Yeah.
So yeah...
-I see... But when I was younger,
It's not like I was just childishly sitting on the Famicom playing all day.
-Well-
-Well, y'know...
I'd visit friends and borrow software I wanted to try,
-Ahh...
and then bring it to someone else's house and play it...
-Hmm.
-Oh man, oh man, oh man. That sure was an era.
-Um...
-My parents really didn't like that,
But now, uh...
Now that I'm a parent, it's something I don't like either.
-[laughter]
I wonder what I'll do if my own child turns out like that.
-Yeah...
-Uh-huh, so those feelings you had of wanting to do it,
you realised that, in a sense,
-Yes.
through creating this work of self-expression.
-I guess you're right...
Right.
Now, moving along,
-Right.
Uhh...
Prior to this event, I saw a lot of Cave Story fan works,
for example, on Pixiv, and Niconico Douga,
The fans have really made lots of great illustrations,
or music using Organya,
-Yes, there is... Yeah.
It seems like derivative work is pretty popular,
-You're right, yeah...
Amaya-san, how do you see these fan works?
-Well, let's see...
When the game finished development,
I didn't wanna look at my-
I just didn't even want to look at Cave Story at all anymore.
Which, yeah,
-Is that so?
I mean, I don't even know how many times I test-played it, trying to iron out bugs...
-Yep.
-Yeah...
-Mhm.
Fixing bugs was not fun at all, haha...
After that, the rewarding moment came when...
people posted on my BBS saying they liked it, or cleared it...
As for fan works, uh...
I've seen them, and...
it's like, "Ah, so this is how other people see it".
ano shinsensan??? ga atte...
-Yeah...
And it's really well done. I'm no illustrator,
but there's so many people drawing Cave Story way better than me.
So yeah... It makes me happy.
-Really, fans of Cave Story have popped up everywhere, and are spreading far and wide.
-Yeah.
-You're right.
-Oh and yeah, the characters, they're super popular,
could you tell us a bit about how you made them?
-Right...
-Well uh, let's see...
You know, in the beginning, uh,
I hadn't thought of anything in particular. I just added characters,
one by one as necessary, and they turned out the way they are now.
-meccha kekkou game no atama kara junban ni kansei saseteku shuhou desu ka?
-sore ga ne, atama no bubun dake chigaun desu yo
-Hmm.
-I see.
Uhm...
At the moment, um,
I forget what exactly I'd finished with,
but in terms of the program, the source, the characters I made,
Considering all that,
the first thing I made was the Egg Corridor.
-Ah.
-Ah, so that was the first thing?
-So uh...
-Well, after I restarted development.
-I've been wondering about this for a long time now, but in Cav-
-Yes?
In the Egg Corridor, there's those elephants, right?
-There are.
-Yep.
They kinda, well, they seem pretty different from other enemy characters...
-Oh yeah, about that.
I was still developing with that Ikachan feeling...
-"Feeling"?
-[laughter]
Well, the characters in Ikachan are kind of simple...
Yeah, I just drew lines for the eyes, no frills here...
-Teapot-looking elephant.
-You're right... So...
I started development from there,
sono hanashi no tsuzitsu mawaseru uchi ni
-Hmm.
mae ga fuete andake ni nattete ??? desu ne
-??? zenbu tsuku dakedo
koko ni narithka tarinai kara mata ta???
-Ah, yes,
that's right.
But when you think of Cave Story,
the first scene that comes to mind, I'm sure,
is of when you're outside, right?
-Ah, yes. Well,
game wo tsukuru no ni doushite mo story mae ni deru to
tou scene janai kana tte iu no ga atte
However,
I had this part in mind,
that scene where Moonsong plays,
-Yeah.
where you climb the Outer Wall,
So about that...
I knew I just had to put it in.
-Ah.
-Mm.
The music,
-So this part was in your head from the beginning?
-Yes.
-Right, this part we see here,
this scene in the game,
this... Yeah, the fans seem to have drawn it a lot...
So yeah, about this part...
Y'know, with other games,
there's uh, quite a few, well,
scenes where the music plays, and you're just staring,
-Mm, yeah.
I wanted to try that out myself,
-I get it.
and that became what we see there in the game, uh,
so that's how I made this Moonsong scene. And, you know,
-Right.
-Ahh.
quite a few people lik-
-You could almost say that the whole game was made
made just to realise this one scene, no?
-...You're right, you know, the motivation came from the music,
from the feeling of wanting to put in that scene, yeah.
-You mean the development followed from the music?
-That's right. Basically,
In the end, you gotta have some section you really like,
-Right, right.
so you work hard for it, yeah...
-I've been wondering this for a long time, but...
Mimiga, I can pretty much, understand, uh, what they are,
Mimiga are basically some kind of animal...
-Right.
But... Just what is Balrog?
-[audience laughter]
-About that...
-There's lots of theories out there, yeah?
-Mm.
-Yeah.
Well, in the beginning,
He was supposed to be soap.
So uh...
-He's soap?
Before restarting development,
Um, you remember those bubble guys we saw for a bit earlier?
-Ah, in the Alpha version we saw an excerpt of earlier?
-Yes, that's right. So um, he's supposed to be like...
he's like the boss of the soaps, Balrog is.
I mean Puu.
And he uh,
The mimiga living in the caves...
He uh, he eats them...
-Woah, so he was a really bad guy!
-Yeah, he was a bad guy, and...
-He's quite a ??? guy, it does get pretty nasty in the script.
-Right, like...
like to the point of morbid,
-Right, right, like "put them in water" and stuff...
Prepare Mimiga by putting them in water,
and they'll taste better, or stuff like that...
-Pretty nasty.
That's how it was, yeah.
-So, he wasn't a toaster?
-Yeah, he's not...
-So...
Yeah?
-Do you... like soap?
-Uh, yeah, I like soap.
-So about Puu...
-Hm, so why soap?
-Yeah, the idea of making soap characters...
-Well, that's uh...
Um...
It's convenient, see? Uh,
Um, the collision detection, it...
-A-ha.
You get what I'm saying, right?
Like the collision detection, if you use rectangles...
-[laughter]
In every way, um...
I mean, with circular characters,
if something hits the 'corner', it's a problem...
Also, I wanted to be able to stand on top of enemies,
so that's how it went...
-So...
You get it?
-Like, I get that,
Oh you do?
but still, man, soap? Really?
-[audience laughter]
-Oh, there's that too,
um,
So in a 16x16 sprite,
-Mm?
if you draw a circle,
-Uh-huh.
and then just draw a dot in it, it looks like a bubble.
And that image of a bubble, I really like it, you know.
-I see.
So, I...
-So you wanted to make bubbles.
So I wanted to make bubbles.
And so I really...
-Ohhh, because it's soap, right?
You're right, it's soap, so it makes bubbles...
-Right.
You can really feel that roundness in the bubbles,
-Hmm, yeah.
despite it being pixel art,
feel the, um...
Humidity?
-Hum...
-Huh?
-M-moisture.
-[laughter]
-Humidity, hah.
-Um, yeah, anyways...
So that feeling really came across,
so I started spamming bubbles everywhere.
-Haha.
-I used a lot of bubbles in Ikachan, too.
-Oh, yeah.
I like bubbles, yeah.
-Right since your student days, no? It's a recurring theme.
-Uhh...
-Um, yeah, I guess you're right, haha.
I hadn't noticed. Also, this is something I'd forgot about,
but uh,
there was this game called Doggy Wyvern,
-Oh yeah, yep, yeah.
it's a game featuring a dog flying through the air,
let's see, where was this...
Hmm... Where is it...
-Doggy...
-Was this something you made fairly long ago?
-Yes, it is...
So this is actually from before Ikachan,
and at the time I wasn't worrying about storage capacity,
so I made the soundtrack in WAV format,
-Hmm...
-This is that software you had made for a
school project, right?
-Yes, you're right, yeah. Um,
-Huh?
You made a game for a school project?
-That's, well, we formed a group at school,
-Well, see, we uh...
and we produced this one game,
and - oh, there it is!
-Lots of stories behind this thing, hehe.
-Huh, the icon looks kind of like King, doesn't it?
-Uhh...
I think it should work this way...
-Ah, it's running.
-Yeah.
So in this game, the soundtrack was made with
a nice music software called XGWorks, by Yamaha.
-Oh, yes.
and to really let its sound shine,
[TL Note: 'kikaseru' can mean either 'to make someone listen to...' or 'to take advantage of and bring out the best in...'. Both meanings work here, was it a pun?]
-I know about it.
-Mhm.
I saved the files in WAV format,
which now meant one song was like 3 MB,
-Haha.
which is kinda...
Well, let's see if this runs further...
So this is, well...
-Ooh.
-This looks neat! What's going on here?
-Well, this is parallax scrolling we have here, and uh...
-Bubbles!!
-[laughter]
-Bubbles!
-There's bubbles!
-It's bubbles.
-Yep, sure are bubbles.
-This...
Yeah, there's bubbles, huh...
I'd forgotten about it, but it was from here,
starting around this time, that I started using bubbles in stuff...
-So we actually had to make this game as a team,
that's the sort of project it was.
But in reality, well, the other people in the team...
uh, they didn't really do anything. Pixel worked by himself,
and ended up making it all on his own.
-[chuckle]
???
When it was time to present in the huge [exhibition] hall,
-In the end I wasn't able to finish this, though, various problems came up...
-Well, yeah.
-Huuhh...
-But y'know, what I'm seeing here seems plenty.
Like, I'd play it. It's got enough polish already, feels like.
-Mhm.
-You think so?
-Yeah, honestly. It looks really interesting.
-Now, this is a dog here, but...
A dog flying in the air like that...
Normally, that's unthinkable, right?
But in a game...
You can rush in with enthusiasm,
and make what you want. So I made this dog,
-I see.
this dog that flies through the sky.
Now, why you're hurling fish, or why the enemies fall apart like that,
I have no idea-
-[laughter]
Ah! And we're done.
ma ??? game wo...
-Huh.
-Ohh...
-Do you like animals? The Mimiga, too,
now that I think of it, are animals...
-Ah, animals, huh? Well, ever since I can remember,
when drawing a picture, if I think about drawing a human,
the clothes, and fingers...
-Uh-huh.
you have to draw all that.
-Ah, true.
And that, I just can't draw it.
-Wait, that's the reason? That's why animals?
-With animals, you don't need to draw clothes.
And even if you do, you can keep it simple.
Like put everyone in a suit or something.
Also, you can get away with not drawing any fingers at all.
-Yeah, you can just make it all fluffy.
-Yep.
-So yeah, I like animal characters.
??? ma sore mo atte kekkyoku mimiga ya to omoundesuyo
-Right.
If I'd drawn humans, then I'd end up making a game with nothing but humans, I think.
-I see.
-I actually, well...
When I played Cave Story for the first time,
I kept thinking that a cute character would show up sooner or later.
Then as I went on, WHAM, Kazuma showed up.
And then WHAM, Kazuma again.
-???
-Yeah.
-[laughter]
???
tsukutte to wakaranain desu yo ne sono kankaku wa
-Huh.
-Yeah...
-Well,
With that, I think this is a good place to...
-Yes?
-Ok.
-Oh, it's been that long?
-Yep. Well, it's been, hmm, just about an hour since Part 2 started.
-Ahh, alright...
-So, shall we have another recess here?
-Ok.
-Sure.
-Yeah.
-So we'll break for ten minutes,
and... the finale is Part 3, right?
Hmm... What was in Part 3, again? "Cave Story-..."
"...- What Awaits"?
That's the name?
-Wasn't expecting that.
-Didn't think that would be it.
-Yeah.
Well,
Uh, so we'll finish by going through "Cave Story - What Awaits",
and compared to what we've heard so far,
uhh...
well, in Part 3, we'll explore a different angle of the story.
Where's Niconico at-
-WOAH, this is sick.
-Well?
-9,000 viewers out there.
-Ah.
-Ooohhh.
-Wooaahhh.
-Thanks a lot, viewers from online!
-Yeah.
-So, on the official site, uhh...
right, there was the popularity contest and stuff that was held,
and we should be seeing the results of that in Part 3,
-Right.
-Huuhh.
-I believe.
-Hey.
-Hey!
-Heeyyy!
-[laughter]
-Lots of "hey"s there.
-Came out delicately, no?
[laughing]
-Yeah...
-Alright, so with that, let's take a ten-minute break!
I'm sure you're thirsty, folks,
-Yes.
so there's plenty of stuff you can order.
And so,
Part 2 has now come to a close.
Good work, everybody.
-Thank you very much.
[applause]
-Thanks a bunch, guys.
-Scuse me, can I get a refill?
-I'm parched!
[INTERVAL]
-Okay.
Alright,
We will now be starting Part 3, uhh...
-Woah.
-[murmuring]
-Wha...
-Umm, okay...?
-What is this?
-This?
Naramura is the artist, you know...
-Umm...
Is it really okay to start off Part 3 like this?
-Scary.
-[laughter]
-This is the introduction?
-Turns out, Part 3 wasn't about "Cave Story - What Awaits".
Uhh, "Cave Story and its People"...
That's what it is.
-Let's redeem ourselves a bit...
-Oh, this is a nice illustration.
-This one?
-Mm.
-Yeah.
Quite the bind, this scene, no?
-It's cool...
-This one, uh,
I drew it as part of work.
-This one?
-Um...
-Ok, one more.
-Huh? Another?
-Here...
-[laughter]
-[audience laughter]
-I put this in again as a prank.
-[laughter]
-So uh...
I'd been thinking I should make some art for this event,
-Mhm.
like this one and the previous one, so I started on that...
-Right.
But well, if you go on the internet and look up Cave Story fanart,
-Yeah?
everyone has the impression that it's a cutesy world.
-Hehe.
-Yeah, totally.
-Oh, i-is that so?
-That's how it's drawn. But...
But if you really think about it, aren't these characters...
...supposed to be killer robots?
-[laughter]
-[audience laughter]
-Yeah, you're right, actually.
-They're killer robots sent from the Surface,
-You're definitely right.
-Ain't that what it's supposed to be like?
-???
-koiha nanda image shita mono ga attari surun desuka?
-Huh?
Oh, well, there's people inside.
-[laughter]
-Ah, I put dots all over the eyes.
???
-Peepholes?
-Yeah, yeah.
-Yeah...
-Okay, so with that, let's start Part... hah...
-[chuckling]
Seriously, is it okay? Starting like this?
Right, let's get down to it. Part 3, "Cave Story and its People".
So, we have, uhh...
Well. I said this earlier, but
we conducted a popularity contest on the official site.
So to begin,
let's announce the results.
-Should we do introductions again?
-Ah. Hey!
-Hey, hey!
-Heeyy.
-???
-Yeah.
-W-we've got 10,000 viewers online.
-10,000? Whew.
-Woaahh.
-Awesome.
-That's amazing.
-Y'all really volunteered yourself to attend this?
-[laughter]
-Thank you for coming.
-??? mina san katte idaito tsugi ni tsunagaru to yobare. ??? desu ka ne
-The next?... Ah.
-True.
-Yeah.
-It's a nice thing, isn't it?
-Yep.
-[laughter]
-Oh, right, um,
The drinks, it seems they're almost sold out,
-Oh.
-I see.
I'd like to try the Toroko for now...
-Ah, let's try a Toroko.
-Please.
-Ok, then, two Torokos, please.
-Oh, make that three, please.
-Four, please.
-Ah.
-[audience laughter]
-Toroko sure is popular, huh?
-sa ma sonna ne? toroko ga hat/kasenai??? nano ka to iu toko mo fukumete
-Anyone here who tried Toroko?
-I think so.
It's the green thing, right?
-With or without red flowers?
-[laughter]
-Without red flowers, I think.
-Not frenzied, right?
-Yep.
-Yeah...
-Anyways, moving on!
With that, let's begin with, uh...
Na...
Oh?
-"Let's begin", was it?
-[chuckling]
-Right.
So we have the Monster popularity poll,
then the Character,
and the BGM-
These are the three popularity polls we ran.
So...
Let's start with the Monster poll.
-Yes, right, just gimme a minute...
Yet again, I'm in a hurry and it's taking forever...
-You're right.
Do your best!
-Okay, I will...
-How long were these polls held, and how many participants?
-???
-Fanart...
Sorry, no, I mean,
The Character popularity poll ran...
About two weeks?
-Mhm, that's how long?
That's how long it was held...
-I see...
-And about 500 people responded.
-Woah, that many people?
-Yep, yep.
Well, not a lot of people were notified,
uh,
I made the announcement on Twitter,
Well, the first was... that guy,
and after that, the bottom spots were in pretty close contest.
Also, at first, it was... Misery vs. Sue.
-I see.
-And there were these two rival factions,
those saying "Misery is cute!",
and those saying "Sue is irresistible!" - these groups were fighting.
-[audience laughter]
-Irresistible?
-And then, in there,
you had Balrog swooping in with a "Hey!".
-[laughter]
-Balrog, man.
-So there was a three-way struggle in the end.
-Yep, yep.
-Ah, I see.
-Well, no matter how it actually turns out,
please enjoy the results.
-True, true. Yeah.
-Yeah.
-Yep. C'mon, show us the Monster results.
-Uhh, hold on a sec...
-[laughter]
kore hanashi na norasaki??? no kekkou muzukashii ne
-tsunagu tame ni maou, ageta no ni, jibun ga shabete-
-Monsters...
-Whoa, woops.
-Alright, alrightie, let's do this...
-What were the monsters, again?
-The monsters, huh...
-boku mo ???
-Yeah. When I took a look at hisuto???
I thought, woah, there's that many?
-[chuckles]
-Mhm.
It surprised me, even.
-There's about 50~60 in all, right?
-You're right.
-de ko kaito suru shimo zenbu oboeteno kanaa to shiginimisu san kedo
-I don't think a single person would know the names.
-Oh, there are. And-
-Well, for a monster popularity poll,
it's good enough to just have known monsters on there.
-Yeah.
So, uh...
-Are we ready to go?
-We're all set.
-Ok, shall we start from #5?
We have #5 to #1 all lined up, right?
-Yep.
Alright, we have... #5!
-#5!
#5 from the monsters...
-This dude!
-[laughing]
-Ah...
I see.
-This thing's a monster?
-Haha.
-Yeah, uh...
-This is a b-
This is one of the bosses, actually.
-Right.
-A mushroom?
-Yeah.
It's small, but it jumps around a lot.
I like it too.
-I wonder how many players this thing killed.
-A whole lot, I'd guess.
-Like, really.
It's really strong.
-Once you kill it, it's an item, right?
-Ah, yeah, you're right.
-Ahah.
-Should it even have been in the poll?
-Well, yeah, it's an item.
Though that's a spoiler...
-Oh, but,
it's not a monster you'd fight normally, right?
-You're right...
The people who picked this,
must be the ones who actually fought it.
-Ah,
-That makes sense.
Listening to this conversation...
-Right.
Moving on, #4!
-Yessir, #4...
-Ta-da!
-If you will.
-Critter!
-Oh, this one, huh?
-Critters...
-Looks nothing like what you drew back there!
-[audience laughter]
-This...
If it'd really looked like this, heh,
it probably wouldn't have been #4, haha.
-[laughter]
-This thing, oh man...
-Critters are pretty popular, huh...
-Is colour mentioned?
-There's various... Ah!
Right, the colour...?
-[laughing]
-I guess it was green.
-This one though, often comes in groups...
-Doesn't this... appear in different places with different colours?
-Ah, right,
All of them are critters.
-Are they all critters?
-Mhm.
The big ones are Power Critters.
And power... well,
they're bigger in size.
-Right.
Alright, then...
-This one was #4, huh...
-They show up again and again, so they make a strong impression.
Let's move on to #3.
-You can say everyone knows them, no doubt.
-They can be pretty unpleasant, huh?
-Yeah, if you shoot, then they jump...
-Right...
Yeah...
-Right, then, #3...
-If you will.
-Yessir, coming right up, #3...
-Ta-da.
-Oohhhh.
-Ohhhhh.
-Ooohhhh.
-Boss ga hajimete,
??? ah mappi ni omomokousa mitai na mono ka
Right.
-This is another boss that's... pretty strong.
-This boss...
It has quite an impression on the story's flow, eh?
-You're right, you feel bad for the situation here...
-Mhm.
-Me too, when I got to this point in the game,
-Yeah?
-Foroo nai janai desuka
-Right...
-Yeah, you're right.
-jibun ???
-Right. When she dies,
she just disappears without saying a word...
-???
-[laughter]
-You're right.
-That's right.
She's been through so much, and in the end...
-King actually has a line there, if only "Oww" or something...
-kore demo touji kara, ichiban saisho kara, mou noun??? dattan desu yo ne
-Huh...
-Hmm...
-So, it was like, "what now?"
bokura mo minna, kore wa moun??? no hou ga zettai
-Ahh...
mou kokoro ni sasatte
-Mhm...
-kanfa??? demo koitsu dake naranai
-naranai
-sou desu ne
-ah sasuga ni demo ???
-[laughter]
nanimo nai dayo??? taoshimashita tte
sore wa chotto ???
-itteba kotae wa??? nandomo nandomo taoshimashita
-[laughter]
-It was painful.
-Yeah, that tracks...
-But you know, all of a sudden,
the tone of the story changed here.
-Ah, ???
???
-And then, with that sadness still fresh,
you walk outside, and Balrog's theme starts playing.
-[laughter]
-Totally changes the mood, huh.
-Jumps you from above, right?
Yeah.
-Right, so, let's move on to #2?
-Yep. #2, coming right up!
-Ah, huh...
-A Night Spirit, eh...
-Oh, this huh?
-This one seems a bit different, no?
-Hmm...
-This thing is...
kinda...
It's a small fry, basically.
-Ah, right.
-Bit big for a small fry, no?
-[laughing]
-True, the sprite is bigger than Balrog, I think.
-Is this...
Is this a cat?
-What is this, actually?
-What indeed... A ghost?
I tried drawing a ghost, but...
The shape of the head does seem fit for a cat...
-[chuckling]
-Fit for a cat, hehe.
-I do like this sort of shape for cats, yeah.
-Ah, wait, isn't this what you'd been wanting to draw at the start?
-Right.
You're going outside for the first time,
that scene. This character wasn't yet conceived, right?
-I think I first had Moonsong, and that scene,
-Mhm.
and then chose this character based on that.
-Right, hmm.
-I think choosing this for #2 sounds about right.
-Had you planned on putting these in from the start?
-Eh, um...
-[laughing]
Ah, this isn't...!
Just climbing up felt a little bland by way of design...
-Hence these flying enemies...
-So these... yeah, kinda,
I put them there to challenge you.
There wasn't anything there, at first.
-Hmm.
-Mhm.
-If this is #2, then what might...
...what might #1 be?
-o sou totsuka nai deshou
-#1 is...
-#1 is...?
haha, sou totsukanai desuka ne
Alright, #1...
Don't think it's made an appearance yet, has it?
-Yeah, guess not.
-Right.
-Alright, for #1, let's get some fanfare!
-Oh, that so?
-Yep, if you please.
-[drum roll]
-[laughing]
-And now, coming in at #1, is...
Monster X!
-Ahh...
-Oohh...
-Woahh!
-[applause]
-So it's this...
-So it's this?
-So it's this!
-So it's this.
-[chuckling]
-[applause]
-You say you liked this?
-I see.
-I see, huh!
-So this guy, I think...
I think a fair few people gave up here.
-Hmm.
-[audience laughter]
-It can be hard to figure out the weak point.
-For sure.
Its HP doesn't decrease in the beginning, until you destroy those...
Well...
Yeah, honestly, this guy is...
-It does kinda make you panic at first, eh?
-kawaii tekita cho shibaite mattetara totsuzen ???
-Haha.
I wasted like, an hour-
...no sorry, a month, on its movement.
-Woah, it took that long?
-I spent quite some time drawing a caterpillar-like motion,
so I'm pretty happy this was #1 on the poll...
even though it doesn't talk.
-It's pretty subtle, huh? Now that I see it I can tell,
but caterpillars move kinda diagonally...
-Yeah uh, you try it out, and you can tell diagonal makes sense...
It was a pain...
-When you defeat it, an animal pops out, right?
-Right, a cat pops out.
What's with that?
-What indeed, I wonder...
-[laughter]
I mean, I kinda just made it on a whim,
I didn't even really have an explanation to myself. And a lot of things,
-So that cat...
-Yes?
The cat... where and why does it enter the machine?
-Well, you know how a Bakeneko transforms its appearance using magic...
[TL note: A Bakeneko is a shapeshifting cat-like spirit in Japanese mythology.]
-Ah,
-Right, right, I see.
-So, I guess it's magic?
-[audience laughter]
-Oh come on.
-You just came up with that, didn't you!
-Don't just make stuff up!
-[laughter]
-Ah, so the cat's not inside?
-That's right.
The machine transforms?
-This stage was a labyrinth built to protect the Core within,
-Mhm.
-Right.
And in that, Monster X was, uh, established,
-Established, haha.
-established as a mysterious machine.
-It was basically completed in that order, was it?
-Huh...
-That's right...
I mean, if it's not a swords-and-sorcery kind of world,
-Mhm.
if you see something funny like that out of nowhere,
-Right.
that's just sloppy, yeah?
-The boss's, what do you say, um, action...
The way it follows you, and reverses,
the projectiles that fly around...
-Right.
Did you have any other ideas in mind when designing this boss?
-Well, when I was making it, I didn't think of anything beyond what you see now.
-Hmm.
-Now, as for why this got to #1,
I'm pretty sure it's cuz of the trauma it gave everyone.
So during the questionnaire, in the comments,
Ah right, I mentioned it would be good to leave comments too if possible,
-Ah...
-Mhm...
and every last one of them said Monster X gave them trauma.
-[laughter]
-I am so sorry.
Yeah...
-Yeah.
-So with that, let's...
-Thank you very much.
-Right.
-Right, to continue,
Should we go with the BGM or the Character poll?
-I think going with BGM would be...
-Yeah. Let's save Character for last...
-Let's save Character for last.
-Right.
-I've got BGM lined up already, so...
-Oh, go ahead then.
-[laughter]
-sono kain wa chotto tsunagi itaraite desu???
-Right.
-Right...
-The BGM, well... I really like it, too,
and I just couldn't choose from it.
-Ahh.
-Uhh,
Well, true... This poll doesn't ask for just one favourite, yeah.
-Mhm.
-Right...
-So uh, well..
I think this is better,
-Mhmm.
I mean, compared to just picking your favourite,
-Right.
you're selecting multiple songs that you like, at once...
-Yeah.
-Niconico Live is kinda blowing up now...
-Last Battle's popular, eh?
-Ah, Grasstown - I like Grasstown, too.
-Oh yeah.
-Is that so...
Hmm...
-I like the theme from, uh, Snack.
-Huh?
-Which?
-Eh?
-Uh, Snack is, um...
[TL note: Snack as in Snack Bar/Cocktail Bar, i.e. Sand Zone Residence]
-Oh, Snack.
It's from the stage where you meet Curly Brace.
-Ohhh, yeah! I get it, I get it.
-Yeah...
'Cockroach Theme', someone says...
-Oh, hahaha.
Well, that would be the characters' location...
Right?
-Oh, the cockroaches, huh?
-Mhm.
The cockroaches, well, the labyrinth...
-Right.
-Looking at the comments here,
-Yeah?
Last Battle and Running Hell...
shuuman no kkosen shita omoide aru tokoro wa tsuyoi ne
-Ahhh, hmm, well...
-I guess those game-like songs that get your blood pumping are fun.
-Game tracks are definitely,
asonda kaisu stage ja nankai ???
-Ah, yes. When you look at what songs are popular,
ramura toka theme ???
attan sa ranking de???
-The songs that get popular are usually the starting ones,
The songs that you hear a lot grow on you.
-and the ones you hear so much, they give you trauma.
kikasatatte??? iu kansou de
-Alright, it's all ready.
-Right.
-Then let's start with #5.
Are we playing the songs too?
-Ah, yes, we are playing them.
-Oh, cool, let's have fun.
Right.
Without further ado, then, #5...
-We're starting with #5.
#5 is this song:
-Yes.
[Main Theme plays]
-Hm.
-Oh, this is #5.
-I've heard this so much.
-Yeah, the idea was, you listen to it on the title screen,
and then later when you get to the stage it plays in-game, you're like, oh that's nice.
-Oh, yeah.
I've used this method since Ikachan, actually.
-I see!
Ikachan's title screen theme also shows up in the endgame there,
-Huh.
which makes for a nice feeling.
-Mhm.
-It plays when the place is crumbling, right?
So just this song-
This song is really long, though.
-Yeah.
I bet there's a lot of people who liste-
who didn't listen to the whole thing.
-It played earlier, just before we started this event,
-Ah, yes.
It didn't play the whole song, though,
-Ah, you're right.
I just heard a little, I think.
-Right.
The melody at the end of the song is amazing, though.
-I...
-It's kinda sloppy...
-I wondered if the Plantation theme was a different version or something.
-Ahh...
-The title screen's theme...
-You immediately press 'Continue' at the title screen.
The song changes...
You can only hear the prelude, basically.
-Yeah.
-Right.
Let's move on to #4, yes.
-Ah, yes, please.
-Yup.
Uhh... one moment if you will...
-Let's see what #4 might be...
-Now, #4... This is definitely a trauma song, eh.
-?
-And what do you mean by that...?
-I should really go easier on you guys...
-Haha.
-Alright, #4, coming up!
-Yes!
#4 is... this song:
[Running Hell plays]
-Ah.
-Ahh...
-What's with this-
-Yeah, this tracks.
-[laughter]
-Oh man, I did this too.
-This stage was made such that it's fine if you don't clear it...
-Mhm.
-Man, how many times have I heard this song by now?
-Yeah...
-Honestly, yeah,
When I was playing, I probably listened to this for like,
ten hours, or thereabouts.
-Haha.
-And thus traumatised, I had some questions for Amaya-san.
-Yeah.
-Yeah, actually, I got a lot of questions on my BBS, saying, "Is it ok if I can't clear this stage?"
-Uh-huh.
So I felt the need to say,
that yeah, it's fine if you don't clear it.
And my sincere apologies.
-Yeah...
-Well, uh...
It really is hard...
-???
-So in the DSi version, you can choose your difficulty, right?
-Right.
So, to be honest, if I were playing the DSi version,
on Normal mode, with the red cap,
???
And this is because in Easy mode, with the yellow cap,
toriaezu clear dekiru n de, boka??? debug sore de yattemashita
-Ahh...
-Hmm...
Ending made ikeru wake desu ne
-Yes, yes, exactly.
Yeah...
-Yeah.
-Well, now...
-It's that hard, isn't it.
-Yeah...
-Shall we move on to #3?
-Let's move on, yeah.
-Yup.
-Hmm... #3...
#3, was it... Ah, there it is.
-Moonsong hasn't shown up yet, huh...
-What rank is Moonsong at? Probably #1, I bet.
-There was a lot of talk of Moonsong on Twitter, yeah.
-There's also been a lot of people remixing Moonsong.
-Huhhh...
-Alright, here it is...
-Let's see it.
Well then... #3 is this song:
[Last Battle plays]
-Ahh...
-Ohh...
Yeah, this one was mentioned earlier,
on Niconico. This is Last Battle.
Right?
Well, the final battle is where you'd be most pumped up.
-You're right, yeah.
It makes sense players who cleared this part would like this song.
-Mhm.
-While making the game,
I didn't really think about how tired I was making the player near the end.
-Ah...
-You think about stuff like that as a gamedev?
-I didn't think about it, no...
By the time they clear the game, they must be dripping with sweat...
-Just instakill them right after, haha.
-[laughter]
-sore wa gigono??? no yarikata janai
-Well, I mean, this sorta thing, like...
-It's true, it's pretty sudden...
-It's just one battle after another, isn't it.
In the video, before this,
just before the Las- the final fight,
when you fight Misery and the Doctor,
there's no health refills, right,
-Oh, yeah.
so by the time you get to the next fight,
your head's drooping the whole time...
-Uh-huh.
-Haha.
-Like, "Man, I've had enough of this..."
-"What am I even doing here?"
-Well, y'know, I bet a lot of people were like,
-Yeah?
"I've got work tomorrow, but I'm gonna keep going till I beat this boss."
"I'll play until morning,"
or like, "asa ga ??? tsukou toshite tachiagaru".
-Yeah,
-So thanks to stuff like that, you'd hear this song
over and over again, and come to like it.
Or so I think.
-Right.
-Yeah. So...
-Right, so, #5 was the Title Theme,
and #4 was...
the super difficult final stage that requires certain conditions to unlock,
and #3 was Last Battle.
Now #2 is...
-#2 is... What, indeed?
-#2 is...?
Uhh let's see, it's...
Puu...
-Well, y'know, my...
-My favourite song hasn't shown up yet.
-That so?
-#2, hmmm...
-Ikeya-san, which song do you like?
-Hmm, well...
I wonder if it'll show up, but my favourite's gotta be...
Egg Corridor.
-Ahh...
Oh, in the ending, too,
it plays at the end.
-Oh yeah, it does.
-Mhm, on to #2...
-Yes, please.
-Right, #2 is this song:
[Mischievous Robot plays]
-Ah!
Hah.
-Showed up, eh?
-Suspicious!
-???
-Yeah.
-This song is titled Mischievous Robot, right?
-Yes, uh,
I made a really bright, upbeat song,
-Right.
and based on that mood, I called it Mischievous Robot.
Oh, but this also shows up during the end credits.
-Ah, yes, you're right.
-Mhm...
-Yeah, this song-
-So the song came first after all, and then the name...
-Yes, this one too is quite...
-Yeah.
-I mean, if you started with the title...
-You'd think the song'd just be called "Egg Corridor" too...
-You're right.
-Ah, you're right...
Well, when I made this song, the level wasn't completed yet,
this much I remember.
-Huh...
-I see, I see.
-Well, another thing, uh,
when you go to Egg Corridor a second time, when it's all destroyed,
initially, this song played there too.
-Hahaha.
-Oh, yeah.
-And that upbeat tune's playing, but the dragons are all like, "Roaarrr!"
-Ehh...
And we were like, yeah okay, maybe this is kinda weird...
And so the BGM there was remade, more sombre.
-???
-Is that so?
-??? ichiyou sono shussei mo atte
-Yep.
-Hmm.
ima kekkou pittari ??? desukedo
-Right.
Well, I'm happy that this song showed up.
-[laughter]
-Ahaha.
Now, I wonder what #1 is...
-I wonder...
-Okay then, #1...
-Yes, please.
-Drumroll, folks.
Yes.
-Yes please.
[Drum roll]
Alright, it's here, it's here...
Alright, #1 in the BGM popularity poll is this song:
[Moonsong plays]
-Ah...
-Ahh...
Yeah.
-[applause]
-I knew it.
-Ah, this song...
-I'm happy too, now.
-Amaya-san mo, suteyattari??? janai desu ka kore wa
-Yeah, true... I am glad that this song was popular.
-Truly...
This song is mo gyatta???
-Folks in the audience here mostly know, I'm sure,
but for anyone who hasn't seen it before,
it's from fairly late in the game,
-Indeed.
uhh, this scene here, I mean.
Uhh...
Up until this point, Cave Story has been happening within caves,
but now you see the moon suspended in the sky,
the clouds drifting past at great speed,
and the Night Spirits from earlier floating after you...
It's a wonderful, dream-like scene.
And in the background, this song, Moonsong, plays.
-Will you abandon the island, or will you stay and fight?
-Yep, yeah.
This is where you make that choice.
It's a bit more of a... serious point in the story.
-Yeah.
-So earlier, uh,
when I was corresponding with you on Twitter,
you were saying basically you made Cave Story for the sake of this song?
-Yeah, kind of.
-So, in the version from before the development reset, too,
this scene was actually there, along with the song.
-Oh, I see.
This is also the path that leads to the, uh,
the Plantation, yeah.
-Mhm.
-Yeah.
You follow this path and come to the Plantation. And well, this place...
Um, the development reset occurred
right around the beginning of the mid - no, endgame.
-I see.
-Cave Story has a lot of variety in its soundtrack, doesn't it?
-True... Like here, it feels empty, and the tone changes.
-Oh, that's true, yeah.
-Like, there aren't any action scenes with a quiet song.
-Songs all have a place.
-Hmm, yeah.
-I guess you're right, yeah.
-But honestly, yeah. It was with this song,
with this image in mind, that uh,
that Cave Story was developed, basically.
In that sense, it's a very symbolic scene.
-True...
It's only fitting, then, that it took first place.
-Indeed.
-Right. Moving on...
-Let's proceed to the Character poll, shall we?
-Alright, let me get it ready, yeah?
-Okay, then, another visit to... Niconico Live!
-[chuckling]
-Hey!
-Heyy!
-Heeyyy!!
-[audience laughter]
-Oh, they're not here.
-Big upset.
-What's with 'em?
-Oh, they're here, they're here.
-Oh, wow.
-Wow, cool...
-Some sort of pattern hiding in there...
-Um...
-Why exactly does he say "Hey"?
[TL note: He's referring to Balrog, whose catchphrase in the original script is just "Hey!"]
-Hm.
-Uhh... Hmm. Yeah, why does he? I don't remember...
-[laughter]
-I just put it in at first,
and then didn't really have a reason to change it...
Divine inspiration, I guess...
-Divine inspiration? Lol.
-That divine element was pretty strong, though.
Even with passengers, he isn't fazed.
-Ah, when developing,
I couldn't help but see aspects that needed more work.
-Right.
But now, when I look back on it myself, I do think it's a good game.
-Mhm.
tabun demo sore wa no jibou no naka no sekaikan ga yappari
arete no shikkari shiteru kara to omoun desu yo ne
soko kara nori ga atte mo burenain desu yo ne
-So, does he...
Does he normally talk like that?
Or...?
-Yes, exactly, he's always been like that.
-Meaning...?
-Saying "Hey!" as an introduction?
-Oh, I wouldn't go that far.
-Oh, no, no, I myself, sonna page no ???
-Hm, although, sometimes he breaks down.
-[laughter]
-The text can be pretty weird, huh?
-Oh, yeah, it is.
-Ahh, that's probably because...
-??? da to omoimasu
...because I suck.
-Y'know, I kinda wanted to do a popularity poll for the text, too...
-Uhh...
-So about the text, the script was compiled and put together,
by some people on the site,
-Oh...
-In the dialogue...
-serifu chuu arunde omoshi??? naka chance ga areba ne
??? chance kedo mo
serifu ranking toka zehi zehi toka timing deatte itadakitai nano omoimasu
-What does Ma Pignon say when you defeat him, again?
-He says something funny, right?
-Oh yeah, he does.
-After defeat?
-After defeat.
-Not "Aah!" or something?
-sonna ??? janakute
-"You want to eat me?!" was already pretty weird.
-[laughing]
-Haha, true, definitely. It was a bit of a...
-Yeah?
It was some loopy dialogue.
-Uh...
-True.
Monologue?
-Yeah, just straight-up, no lead in, no small talk.
-And then he's like, "Die!!" at the end.
-I just saw Balrog saying "Hey!" float past onscreen.
-Really?
-You did?
-Look, look, here.
[TL note: This is a Balrog ASCII art emoticon that was sent in the comments: [ ¢_¢ ]ノHey! ]
-Hmm?
-Ooh.
-Oh you're right.
-Here, see?
-Ah, ichikyou de???
-Mhm.
-[laughter]
-Yeah, so... There were various...
-Right?
-Okay...
-[laughter]
[TL note: For context, the Balrog emoticon was now repeatedly reproduced in the comments.]
-Thanks!
-This is super cool. That's the thing with Niconico,
this aspect of it, it's like a meeting ground of sorts,
-Woah.
-[audience laughter]
it brings people together...
-You're right, yeah.
-Okay, guys, you can go easy now!
-[laughter]
-Whew. So with that,
-Yep. Let's move on to the Character poll.
if things are ready...
-Yeah.
-Oh right, let's.
-That's right.
Haha, I almost forgot we were doing the poll thing.
-Okay, okay, I get it, lol.
-Right...
-Alright! Character popularity poll...
...Wait, how many characters were there, again?
This is again a large category, eh?
-There were quite a few, yeah.
-There are, also, I forgot to put him in the questionnaire.
-The protagonist?
-Yep, I forgot the protagonist and some others.
Haha.
-So, we good to go?
-Yep, let's start.
-#5...
-#5.
-Yes, please...
-Yes, #5 in popularity from the Cave Story cast is...
-Ah, the protagonist...
-Oh! It's the protagonist!
-Even though you forgot to put him in?
-azukki??? kara ne nandaro
Why do this to him?
-Woah there.
-The protagonist...
-Really taking the dialogue into consideration.
-Hmm, yes.
-You forget about the protagonist's existence, right? I mean,
there's nothing special-
In the normal - the first route, his name isn't even revealed,
he's quite a forgettable character...
Heck, the popularity poll,
he probably forgot about it, like Nakamura-san did.
-Hm, if Nakamura hadn't forgotten, would he have placed higher?
-Hmm, who knows?
-Yeah... who knows...?
-Ah but you know, as the creator,
it should be kept in mind that the protagonist is, after all, just the player,
-Ah.
that's how it is.
So I'm kind of like, well, I guess I'm glad he didn't place first.
-I see, hmm.
-Alright, let's move on to #4...
-Wait, so from here it'll be, uh, the previously-mentioned-
-Ah, the result of the three-way battle, right?
-Oh, yes, I wonder how it'll turn out.
-Alright. Uhh, three-way battle...
Number...
First and last chance?
-Yep, it is.
-Let's see, we have #4 here. #4 is...
-Yup.
-Ah, Misery.
-It's Misery.
-You guys sound miserable! That tracks.
-[laughter]
-No energy?
-Ah, Misery hagane???
-Yeah...
-What kind of character is Misery?
-Hmm, what kind of character is she... Uhh...
A sadist...
...kind of person?
-[audience laughter]
-She's someone who's lived in the cave for a long time, right?
-Yes, um,
In the old version, there was a character called Oscar, who was really brutal,
-Right.
and that character, well,
it remained, now as this evil witch.
-Hm, hm.
-Before the development reset, Misery was actually,
she was actually an ally, you know. Uh,
And well, Sue, Quote, Misery, and also a Professor,
these four people have a photograph together,
And so,
this evil character, Oscar,
his soul kind of remained in this character [Misery].
-Mhm.
So that was #4.
-Yup.
-Right.
-And so with that said, #3 is...
-Alright then, #3 is...
Right.
Let's proceed to #3.
#3 is this character:
-[inhale]
-HEY!
-Ah, hey.
-It's you!
-Made an appearance midway, I see.
-I see. Yeah.
-The soap appears.
-Mhm.
-I see, yep.
-Well,
he is pretty popular, isn't he?
-You're right...
--Uh,
I get that he's supposed to be soap,
but the... rim... around his face...?
-Ah, I kinda... uh, made that so the soap doesn't drip...
-Huh.
-His predecessor didn't have a rim, it was smooth...
-He didn't.
-He didn't, it was all smooth, right?
-Also, his hands...
His hands come out of a slit...
-The slit, right?
Yeah, what's with that?
I never really thought about it too hard, tbh.
-[laughter]
-[audience laughter]
-I just kinda...
I kinda...
He...! Uh, he needs a slit for his hands to move around properly... I guess?
-Mm hmm.
-And suddenly you have a reason, huh.
-It's this box-like shape with a rim,
so it's like a TV or a toaster-
-Yes, exactly, he's pretty toaster-ish.
-Toaster? Slots like these, hmm...
-Huh...
-So that's... bread that's sticking out?
-[laughter]
-[audience laughter]
-I see. Bread sticking out horizontally.
-Haha.
-sanshin na ???
-???, yeah...
-So uh, is Balrog a living thing, or a machine?
-Tough question...
Someone from abroad depicted him as a machine, and showed me...
-I see...
I was like, Hmm, so that's what he's like...
-[laughter]
-It was a revelation.
-Haha...
I mean, he's soap, so it's probably not like that...
As the creator, I can't be accepting other people's fixes for my incomplete work.
-Yeah...
-Alright!
Then...
-Yep, on to #2...
And #2 is...
-Sue.
-Sue...
-Ah, Sue...
-Oh, part of the three-way battle...
-The three-way...
-Yeah.
-What about Toroko?
-Oh, Toroko's not here yet.
-Toroko showed up earlier as an enemy character...
-uchi ni shou nagareta janai desu ka ne
-??? Toroko...
I think a lot of people like Toroko.
-True, true.
-But she hasn't shown up yet.
-Hmm, I think it was like,
-Ah, you're right.
Sue was originally the heroine, actually.
-You're right, yeah...
It wasn't Curly, rather, Sue used to be the main heroine.
-Sue was, um...
-So, the protagonist was the player themself.
But then there's a someone who actually progresses the story - that was Sue.
-Mhm.
And she stumbles around as she tries to find an exit to the cave.
In this setting too, she was a mimiga who didn't get along very well with other mimiga.
Ultimately, part of those characteristics remained in Curly Brace.
-I see.
Well, she's still kind of the main heroine, in a way.
-Right, in a sense.
-Yeah...
-Yeah, Sue's a good character.
-She is.
-Sue de ko nanika ni mezameta mitai na hito mo ???
-What was that?
-[muttering]
-Haha, alright, I get it,
let's move on?
-Alright, haha, yeah.
-Yes.
-Yes please.
-Alright then, uh...
Time for #1...
-Drumroll again, please.
-Drumroll, coming up.
[Drum roll]
-Alright, coming in at #1 in Cave Story's Character popularity poll is...
This character:
-Yup.
[applause]
-More "Ah" than "Oh", wouldn't you say.
-Ah, you're right.
-True, definitely.
-Yeah, this was pretty much expected, I suppose.
-Mhm.
-Y'know, it was a real shock in the beginning.
The first time I finished the game.
-Ahh, when you don't save - uh,
The scene where the Island's going down,
-Yeah...
-Camera panning across, indifferently... Yeah.
-Wait, was there such a scene?
-Yeah...
-So, if you don't save her, that'll happen.
-Yeah, if you don't save her,
-Oh, yeah, yeah.
then moving forward, it shows various stages,
all shaking due to the earthquake.
And in there, you also see Curly, who's collapsed.
-Ohh.
Yeah.
-I mean, now that I think about it, it's pretty wicked.
There's the scene with Toroko, then Curly...
First we can't save her,
we can only stand there, shocked, before moving on,
And in the end, even the Island falls...
-So, when I... When this event came around,
I didn't clear it.
-I see.
-Now, I tried my best,
-Yeah?
and after she collapsed,
I moved a little to the left, and the shutter came down,
and I was like, Whoops, left her behind...
-Ah, I see.
-I didn't follow up on that,
and left that place.
I thought for sure I could go on ahead, and then come back later to save her.
-Yep, yep, I thought that would happen later, right?
-bei ending mukaichaimashita ne ano mama akarui ending wo ???
-Yeah... I'm really sorry.
-[laughter]
-It's true, there's a bit too many deaths.
There is a lot of criticism about this, ano game sunizugi??? deru tte tashikani
atosaki kangaezu ni shinanyoukun??? darou kou nacchatta mitai na
Yeah.
arimashita curly brace tte...
-At first, however,
the True Ending route wasn't there yet, right?
-Yes, that came at the end.
But, in the debugging bulletin board,
...redevelopment? No, I mean,
before they told me to make an ending where you can save Curly,
they were like, it's not so great that the Island has to fall apart completely...
-Yeah,
-abunai koto wo iuteru no ga debaka??? ni omotte
-ah demo s- omae ga yaritai koto wa sore chigainai toka yokatta
-sou, sou ??? ni ne
-ah chotto kangaete dakedo ottette
-isshun de
-ah sou desu ne, hai
-So, tokuhyou su de iu to
eh, mitsudomoe no baisko ga
-dantotsu tte koto desu yo ne
-dantotsu shita ne yappari ne
-souida
-mitsudomoe ni hairanakatta
Well, Curly Brace also has scenes where you fight together with her.
-True. In the comments too,
"That camaraderie of fighting together is nice", they were saying.
kouka okatta character desu ne
-Ah, but that scene is in the end, like in the very end, right?
-Hmm...
-As far as heroine characters go, she's introduced pretty late.
-True, huh.
-The tension is high.
-She moves around a lot when she's following along.
-Hmm.
-Yeah, yeah.
-I would try and dash off ahead on my own.
-That's...
-That's mean!
In videos, too, you see Curly being made to fight basically by herself...
-hoka ni, tatoeba ninki no ato character toka wa dou deshita ka
-Yes?
-Ah, well...
iu to irun desu keredo mo
-Yeah?
-But..
ageru to kiki ga naku naru sou nano de
chotto kore wa mata dokka betsu na kikai de
So uh, I thought we'd do the official announcement.
-Alright, let's go with that.
-sou yo otanoshimii to iu kanji ni ishitada kereba na to omoimasu ne
-So on that note, I think now, the popularity poll is
is wrapping up, so we will bring that to a close.
With that said, I think we're at a good point in time,
finally we have one more,
uh,
there's one more thing to unveil today.
Nakamura-san?
-Ah, yes, uh, we do.
-So... We're good to reveal this now, right?
-Yeah, it's fine.
-So, uh, the DSiWare version's relea-
uh, the release of the remastered version,
In connection with that, an official site has been set up.
-Yes.
So with that, the limited release is-
-This is just going to take a bit longer.
-Ok.
-So, uh...
So, the site that we caught a peek of earlier,
-Yeah.
let's have Nakamura-san show it to us.
-Yup.
Hang on a moment...
-It says "Official Site Opening" there on top?
-Right.
The official site will be handled like, for example,
a continuation of the popularity poll?
-Yeah, I think that would be good, if we can.
-Yes.
-Right, well then, let's enjoy.
-Right. So what we see here is, uh,
this is Cave Story's official site.
Well, this is the admin screen,
uhh,
I can't seem to get into kankidashi???
mi ni ???masen keredo mo
So, now, Cave Story has an amazing fanart scene,
eh, uchi no naramura to iro to shite mashite
and I/he was like, what do you think of this, and uh...
-Um,
Cave Story is, after all, popular as a retro game,
and it was made in pixel art,
-Hmm, you're right.
and well, lately, you're seeing that if a game is pixel art, its homepage will be pixel art too,
-Hm, true.
-So, well,
Just like most of the pe... like those who are here with us today,
I played Cave Story once fairly long ago,
and then hearing it's coming out on DSi, I thought I'd try playing it again...
-Hmm.
-Yeah.
And when the music started playing in this part here, the memories came rushing back,
saisho ni omise shita movie nanka mo
dsi deta kara konya chotto tetsuya de yatte miyou ka tte iu na ???
-Ah.
-Ohh.
-Bed no ue de yattemashita ne? Tashikani.
-Yeah.
-??? desu yo ne?
-And the site itself,
apart from using pixel art...
...can you... uh, go down?
-Scroll?
-Ooh.
-Cool.
-So you see this picture of Curly here,
we thought we'd gather and collect fanart like that,
and thus make a site that was built by everyone.
-I see.
Also, this lettering that says "Fanart" and "Software Info",
that was drawn by Amaya-san.
-Oh, Amaya-san drew this?
-Ah, yes, I did.
-I see.
For the fanart section here,
was there a user-submission entry form, like with this event?
-Right, about that...
-So, I had wanted to implement that if possible,
but uh...
the kokkyoka??? wasn't available to everyone,
and then contacting people individually...
ma kaijakute??? irassharu kata de
ato de o hanasu deki areba, ano, sono toki demo hanashi itadakeraba na to omotte irimasu
-I do think we should continue accepting entries on this site, though.
-Let's have a look at the other pages...
Sure.
-I've been wanting to look at this too, actually...
-Ah, hand-drawn illustrations...
-Ah, yes.
-Amaya-san drew these...
-I drew them, and then...
and then I had Naramura-san make them pretty.
-???
-Yeah, true.
-So...
The people who made the illustrations,
but this was drawn by the creator himself,
so this is official.
-Oh, that's true.
I mean, I can't do 3d modeling...
-Isn't the text... kinda weird?
-Ah, the text...
-???
-Well, I tried to make it "in that style"...
-"In that style"?
-But it got all messy...
[laughter]
What does that even mean?
-janki wa robot yabawi???-
-???
-mimi deshou???
mimi nattemasu ne
-???
-maa fun'iki toshite wa konna... hai
-"In that style"...
-shigoto kara ne,
those who worked on the WiiWare site would know,
koi dame teki surenai to, kankaku wakannai n desu yo ne
de maa, kou iu no, eh, shikakete...ru wake nan desu ne
Yeah.
-About this, also,
right, DSi de no kounyuu??? no shikata de attari to ka,
and the trailer too...
I mean the video shown earlier- er, at the start,
that we made available here, that too...
It was Amaya-san who drew it, in this style.
-[laughter]
-Sorry...
kore kaku made inein??? zutto moteyarou??? dake kaiteta n desu kedo
nanka kawatta koto ga shitakunatta n desu
-[laughing]
beta-beta de sumimasen...
-character nanka mo nanka
amaya-san ga don-don suuki kaete moraereba
hoka no character no shoukai nanka hodoite??? ikeru to omoimasu shi
-hai
-ato wa ano, hantsu vaibi??? ga
kettei shitara, yahari koko de
koukai suru you ni shiyou to omotte ssu???
-Ah, right...
that scene...
-ima kitta???
That scene came into view, right?
-nanka... ???
-On the bottom.
-Um...
-R...right, it was for this reason,
yonmai saite o umenaku ikenakatta n desu kedo
-Ah,
-That's why Naramura-san drew that?
-If you don't ??? quickly, then the top image...
-[laughter]
...will look like this.
-kore no ??? itsu made mo
-It's weird,
Not a great first impression.
-Definitely.
-kyakusei??? mo kawarimasu yo
-demo, kari ni kaita level janai desu yo ne, ano, kou iu kata wa
gaku ni e te kazau??? level ga to omoimasu yo ne, kore
-Right?
-ano, choushi notteru yo ne, yatteru to ne?
-sugeeeee, kowai wa
-[laughing]
Yeah.
-Yeah, so like this, yeah?
-Yeah.
So, when is this opening?
-Hmm, well, we hope...
-Yeah?
-"Coming soon".
-I see, ok.
-Uh, if we work hard, probably around next week.
-Then, please do your best.
-Yessir.
-Mhm.
-Right.
tte iu koto de, ah, maa, illustration touhou mo mata hikitsuzuke boushuu??? shite iku koto no no de
uh, definitely,
all Cave Story fans, I think,
will enjoy the opportunity to contribute.
That said, by the way,
hmm...
it's been about... three hours so far?
Well, about 2 hours and 40 minutes, right?
-Yes.
-Time sure flew by, eh?
-You're right.
-Mhm.
I'm glad it proceeded without incident.
-True, eh? Haha.
Some stuff happened in the middle, but yeah.
-???
-Yes, thanks to all of you, the event appears to have come to a close successfully.
So, what's next,
-Yes.
well,
we have this venue booked for a bit more time,
I think, about an hour, was it? Uh...
-hai ano nantoku jikan ??? kyou yasumenaide jikan ??? de
kono ato fusensha??? to okyakyu-san mazete uchiage yatte mo ii no de zenzen
-Yes.
-We'll be staying behind for awhile after this, too,
you know, just mingle with the attendees a bit...
-???
Ah, the game...
-
-Yes, do stay back if you want to have a go with it.
-[applause]
-Only those present here, though.
-Yes.
-Not you 🫵 guys.
-[laughing]
Ah, yes. Niconico viewers, just wait for the event to finish.
-"Darn it!"
"Darn it!", they're writing.
-Poor things...
-youssugimasu??? yo
-
-Right?
-Yeah.
-
You're right, haha.
-[laughing]
otsukiai to wa nakereba to omoimasu
-Yeah.
-So with that said, now, uhh.....
Man, we really didn't think about how to end this, huh?
For the finale, the trailer...
-Yep!
-Can we see it again?
-Yep, we can do that.
I thought we should end this by watching it.
-Yeah, uh,
As long as it's not Tyrone's video letter, huh?
-Oh that...
-[laughing]
Yeah no we're good.
Yeah, we're good.
Oh you haven't seen it yet? Let's play it in the after-party.
-Oh, no thanks, haha.
are no seisakuhi ??? desu ne
-Ah, ???
-Hm, yeah, there is that production cost.
-okuraretekita n janai no?
-Yeah.
-???
-[laughter]
-Alright...
-Alright, while Nakamura-san is getting ready,
-Yes.
-Yep, yep.
-Yeah.
-Woah, wait, something's making some noise.
-Sorry, seems like a difficult request.
-???
-[laughing]
-Mhm.
-Hm, huh?
-??? Amaya-san
-sou desu ne
-Is it okay if we just ended now?
-Yes please, go for it.
Ah, well, today, um...
Thank you very much for listening about various things,
Thanks to all of you, we were able to get through today,
I'm very grateful, and I hope we get along from now on.
-[applause]
[Main Theme plays]
-And with that, "Cave Story - Behind the Scenes" has come to a close.
So... Folks, thank you for your participation!
-Thank you very much!!
-Thank you!!!
-[applause]
-So, after this, regarding the after-party...
Uhh, Yokoyama-san, how is it going to be...?
-Yes, ah sorry, just a bit more...
ENDED
"Cave Story - Behind the Scenes"
Thank you for coming.